歡迎收看史丹佛大學公開課
Stanford University.
本字幕由志願者義務貢獻
>> All right, well,welcome to Stanford CS193P,
歡迎參加史丹佛大學 2015 年
winter of 2015.
冬季學期的 CS193P 課程
This is lecture number two.
這是我們的第二堂課
I apologize upfront for my terrible voice, we are going
先向大家致歉我糟糕的嗓音，
to try to get through this as best we can today.
我們今天要盡可能去試著克服這個問題
Our topics are two fold.
我們的主題有兩個方面
We're going to continue the calculator
我們將繼續在上一堂課已經開始的計算器展示，
demo that we started, in last lecture and then we're gonna
之後的課程我們會有
have some slides about this model view controller,
一些關於 model view controller，
object-oriented design pattern that we're gonna use in
和物件導向設計模式的投影片
everything we do.
這些都是我們將會使用在每件事上的
When we build applications in this class.
當我們在這堂課中開發應用程式時
All right?
有問題嗎？
So let's get started with that demo.
那就讓我們開始進行展示
Again, here's a slide with the summary of kind of
再重覆說明，這裡是一張總結
the important things we're gonna talk about.
我們接下來要講的重點的投影片
You don't need to read those in advance here,
你不需要提前閱讀這些資料
it's more for reference.
這是參考用的
My slides in general, I post them,
我的投影片一般是，我會貼上它們
it's mostly intended to almost be note taking for you.
主要是為了記下和你們說了什麼
To be able go back and try and
為了你們在復習時可以試著回想起
figure out, whoa, when did he talked about that day?
教授他什麼時候說過有關於這些？
Oh yeah.
What's important, et cetera.
有那些是重要的，之類的
So my slides do tend to be a little bit dense.
所以，我的投影片往往是有點多
I tend to put a little more on them, than,
我會傾向於在上面多放一些內容，
than just bullet items.
不止是列出一些大項而已
But that's because I want you to be able to look back and
但是，那是因為我要你們能夠回頭來看時
kind of get just a little bit more depth to
能夠更多一點深入的讓你回想起
remind yourself what I talked about.
我所說過的這些內容
Okay?
All right, so
好的
this demo, if you'll remember last time, where we left off,
這個展示，如果你還記得上次我們快結束時，
we had gotten the keypad fully working.
我們已經讓按鈕功能可以用了
All right, and we were talking a little bit about properties
好的，我們將要講一些關於 屬性 和
and instant variables and how we had to initialize them.
實例變量，以及如何去初始化它們
And so I'm gonna ask a question right at
我在上次課快要結束時，
the end of lecture, perfect timing.
提出了那個問題，在那個很好的時間點
What about the little outlet that we dragged out
為什麼我們拖出的
that display UI label exclamation point, how come we
顯示 UILabel 的 outlet 後面有個驚嘆號
didn't have to make that equal to something, to start.
以及為什麼我們從一開始不需要將它賦值
And that's where this demo is gonna pick up.
我們將從這個地方繼續上次的 Demo
Okay?
Okay.
Well, let's dive back into this demonstration,
好吧，讓我們深入到展示中來，
where we left off.
接著我們上次講的地方
Which it was this line of code, here.
上次我們在這行代碼結束的
And, we had just talked about the fact that we have to
我們之前講過我們必須
initialize all of our variables in a class,
在類中初始化我們的變量
in any class.
在任何類中都必須這樣做
And, so that's why we need this equals falls here.
所以我們需要在這加個等號
They wanted the equal falls too but we needed it and yet
這裡也需要等號賦值，但是
it didn't seem like we needed one here.
這裡看起來並不需要等號賦值
And why was that?
為什麼會是這樣？
Well, it turns out that this right here,
其實，這裡恰恰證明瞭
even though it doesn't quite look like one, is an optional.
即使它看起來不完全像之前那個，這是一個 optional
And, optionals automatically get equaled nil, given to you.
而且 optional 在你使用之前就賦了 nil
So, you don't actually have to put the equals nil here.
所以，其實你們並不需要在這裡給它賦 nil
So that's why, so this one here is getting initialized.
這就是為什麼這裡已經初始化了
It's just being done automatically for you.
因為它都自動幫你做好了
But, let's talk about the look of this thing.
但是，我們來談論一下這個東西的語法
It's got this exclamation point here.
在這裡有個驚嘆號
And, if it were an optional,
如果它是一個 optional 類型的值
you'd be used to it having a question mark.
你們通常會在這裡看到一個問號
For example, we look at this optional right here,
例如，我們來看這裡這個 optional 的值
current title,
currentTitle,
you see it's String question mark not exclamation point,
你們將會看到這裡 String 是問號而不是驚嘆號，
question mark.
這裡是問號
So what's the difference between a question mark and
那麼，這裡的問號和驚嘆號之間
an exclamation point here?
有什麼區別呢？
And the answer is,
答案是
it makes no difference to the actual type, it's still
對於實際類型而言它們沒有區別，
an optional whose value here could be a UI label.
它仍然是一個 optional 的值，其值在這裡可能是一個 UILabel 類型
But it matters on the usage of it.
但是它們在用法上是不一樣的
And this is purely just kind of
這完全是編譯器
a compiler helping you out thing, here.
幫你把這事做好了
But if we look at when I change this to
但是如果我們將這個驚嘆號改成問號
a question mark you see that some errors appear down here.
Xcode 將會在這裡報出一些錯誤提示
So then let's click on one of these errors, like this one,
那麼，讓我們點擊這其中的一個錯誤提示，比如說這個
and you can see the errors that UI label,
你們會看到這個錯誤提示說 UILabel?
question mark does not have a member named text.
沒有一個叫 text 的成員變量
In other words you can't send text.
就是說，你不能向它發送 text 消息
UI label question mark,
UILabel? 顧名思義
which is what this is and that makes sense because UI label
是一個不確定值的變量，所以也就明白了 UILabel? 是
question mark is an optional and
optional 的類型
obviously an optional doesn't respond to text.
並且顯而易見的，一個 optional 類型的變量不會響應 text 消息
UI labels do, but optionals don't.
UILabel 是這樣的，但 optional 並不會這樣
So, why are we getting this error now when we
那麼回到問題，為什麼之前不會報錯
weren't getting it before.
而現在卻出錯了呢
And how would we get rid of this error?
我們又如何去避免這個錯誤呢？
Well, you could certainly get rid of
嗯，我們當然可以通過
this error by just putting an exclamation point here,
添加一個驚嘆號來避免這個錯誤
that would unwrap this optional.
它會對這個 optional 的變量進行解包
And now this would be an UI label right here and
那麼現在這裡剛好有一個 UILabel
we can send a text.
如果我們要想給它發送 text 消息
And we do the same thing up here.
就可以在這裡也做同樣的事情
We can unwrap it there and we can unwrap it there.
我們可以在這裡對它進行解包，還有這裡也要解包
And that gets rid of all of our errors.
這樣就解決了所有的錯誤
But this kind of an interesting property in that
但是這裡有個很有意思的屬性 display
even though it's not initialized in
因為它並沒有在
the very beginning of a class creation starts out
類最開始創建時初始化成 nil
as nil not set.
而是沒有設值
As soon as as this user interface gets loaded up
一旦這個 UI 界面
by this new controller.
被右邊的視圖控制器加載了
Then this gets wired up, alright, so, that gets
那麼它就會和代碼連接起來，嗯對，只要連接起來
wired up, and this is set, and then this it's set forever.
這個變量就會被設置並初始化，那麼它在整個類中就是永遠初始化過了
So it's really, kinda would be sad if we actually,
但是，如果當我們每次解包時都要寫驚嘆號
every time we used it had to unwrap it all the time.
那真是一件難過的事兒
So these kind of properties that.
所以這些很早前就被設置過屬性變量
Get set very early, maybe not right at creation like
不一定要和這個一樣，在創建時初始化
this one, but very, they get set very early, and
並且，它們設置的時間非常非常的早
then they stay set all the time.
之後一直保持著已設置的狀態
You can, instead of
你也可以
putting a question mark in their decoration.
在聲明的地方用一個問號來代替
We're talking about their decoration here.
我們將在這裡談論他們的聲明
You can put an exclamation point.
你可以在這裡加一個驚嘆號
And what that says is.
那麼它要表達的意思是
This is just an optional, but
這雖然只是一個 optional 類型
always automatically unwrap it so that you don't have to
但它會自動對變量解包，從而就可以不用
put this exclamation point in here.
在這裡加驚嘆號
So I take this exclamation point out.
所以，我把這裡的驚嘆號刪掉了
You can see, it's not generating any errors.
你們可以看到，它將不再報錯
And it's still going to unwrap this display and
它將把 display 轉化成
turn into a UI label.
UILabel
And.
而且
It's still gonna crash your program if for
它還是會由於
some reason the display were nil.
某些原因比如 display 是 nil 崩潰
If you tried to execute this code, that may
如果你執意要執行這段代碼，那是
be impossible because this is the button sending those.
不可能的，因為這裡是由按鈕來發送這些的
So the button wouldn't be here if this hadn't gotten already
這個按鈕不會在這裡除非它被加載
loaded up in the set.
被賦值的時候
But if somehow you had some place in your controller or
但是如果在某種情況下你必須
you were accessing display before this UI got loaded.
在 UI 加載之前你要獲取 display
It would crash, because it is unwrapping this,
它將崩潰，因為它還沒有 unwrap
it's just that you don't have to put the explanation point,
你不需要在這裡寫驚嘆號
it's kinda like auto explanation point.
它會自動解析
And, this is called a implicitly unwrapped optional.
這個就叫做 unwrapped optional
Okay? Implicitly unwrapped optional.
有問題嘛？隱式 unwrapped optional
And it's really only useful for this kind, of property,
在這種情況下它對這類 property 來說有用
that's, set very early, and then stay set, forever.
在創建的時候就賦值，那麼將一直被賦值
It's kind of sugar, really.
這是一點語法的甜頭
Okay, so let's move on
好了，我們將繼續
to the next button in our here.
接著下一個按鈕
Which is going to be an enter button.
它就是 Enter 鍵
Now our calculator does not have an equals sign.
現在我們的計算器還沒有等號
So you're probably used to calculators where you
你們也許通常會這樣使用計算器
say six plus three then when you hit equals it shows you
6 乘以 3，然後你們按等號計算器展示
the result.
結果
This calculator is
我們的計算器會
a little more like a scientific calculator.
更像科學計算器
Has an enter key.
將沒有等號按鈕
And so, instead you put the numbers you want to add or
那麼，你們按你們想相加的數字按鈕或者
divide or multiply or whatever onto a stack and then when you
除以或者乘以無論什麼都將會入棧，然後當你
press the operation keys it pulls them off the stack.
按下操作按鈕的時候，數字將會出棧
So that looks like this, 6 enter 3 times.
比如這樣 6 3 乘
Four, six, enter, three, enter, times.
4 6 enter 3 enter 乘
So the times is going to pull the six and
這個乘法操作符將會把 6 和
the three off the stack.
3 出棧
You could even go six, enter, five, enter, four, enter, and
你也可以按 6，enter，5，enter，4， enter，然後
then go times plus.
按乘以 加
That would multiply the top two on the stack and
它將會把棧頂的兩個元素出棧
then add the last one on.
操作完再將加上棧頂的元素
So we need an enter key here for our calculator.
所以我們的計算器還是需要一個 Enter 鍵
Now, I'm gonna create that enter key in a way that's
現在，我將要通過這種方式創建一個 enter 鍵
actually gonna cause a problem for me in a moment, but
它雖然會引起一些問題，但是
I wanna show you how to resolve that very problem.
我將會展示給你們看如何解決這些問題
So I'm gonna create this enter key by copying and pasting.
那麼，我將通過複製粘貼
This digit key right here.
這裡的數字鍵來創建 Enter 鍵
And I'm just gonna put it in here.
那麼我將會把這放在這裡
Notice that I'm lining these,
我通過這些藍色輔助線
blue lines up absolutely perfectly.
把這些連接起來
I don't want them to be, like it's lined up with that one,
我不想這按鈕放這
but not that one or vice versa.
或者放這裡
I want them perfectly lined up.
我希望它完全對齊
Cuz later I'm gonna spread these out over the whole UI
因為我待會要在整個 UI 中放大這些按鈕
and if I haven't lined these up just absolutely perfectly
如果我沒有將這些按鈕對齊的話
then Expo's not gonna quite know what I want here in Xcode
我將不會知道它們會被
terms of the relationship between these.
Xcode 安排到哪裡
All right so we don't want a three on here, we want to have
好了，我們不希望這個按鈕上還是 3，所以我們需要修改一下
a,enter symbol so I'm gonna go up here to special characters.
一個 enter 的符號，我將輸入一個特殊的符號
This is on in most Mac applications.
這個符號在很多的 Mac 應用中都有
You can go to the edit menu to get special characters.
你們可以從編輯菜單中獲取這些特殊符號
And I'm going to search for
我想要搜索
this one actually, I think that's called a return.
這個特殊符號，我覺得它應該叫 return
Yeah. And these are just
是的，這些都是
Unicode characters right here.
Unicode 字符
And so I want this one that looks,
我想要這個
kind of like a return or enter key.
看起來像返回或者 enter 按鈕的
So I have this.
好了，我找到了
And I'm gonna use the same mechanism we used before,
我將使用之前使用過的機制
which is CTRL+drag.
那就是 CTRL+drag
So I'm just gonna CTRL+drag out here.
那麼我想 CTRL+drag 拖到這裡
And, we're creating an action,
然後，我們創建一個 action
of course, cuz we want this button to send us a message.
當然，我們希望這個按鈕給我們發個消息
I'm gonna call it"enter".
我將叫它 「enter」
That's what it is the enter key
那就是我們的返回鍵.
Now one thing is different about this one,
現在有一件事會有一點不同
if you'll remember when we wired this action up,
如果你記得當我們連接這個 action 的時候
we had the button that was sending it as an argument and
我們讓這個按鈕傳遞給我們一個參數
we don't want that this time.
但是我們這次不需要這麼做
Because there's only one answer key we
因為這裡只有一個返回鍵
really don't need to talk back to the answer key, so
我們並不需要讓返回鍵傳參，所以
we're going to say none right here.
我們在這裡不需要參數
It also doesn't really matter about this type because we're
這裡我們更不用關心它的類型，因為
not going to have an argument so
我們這裡並不需要參數
it doesn't matter what this type is.
不用管它這裡是什麼類型
So connect that.
所以把它們連接
As you can see right here.
你們可以看這裡
We have enter, and it has no arguments.
我們已經有一個 enter 鍵，沒有參數的
Now, what are we gonna do inside enter?
那麼現在，我們將在這個 enter 里做什麼操作？
Well, the main thing we need to do is,
好吧，我們主要要做的是
put whatever number is in this display up here,
把 display 顯示的數字
okay, onto our internal stack.
放入我們的棧中
So, we're gonna need
那麼，我們需要
an internal stack, in a moment, here.
一個棧
Another thing we might wanna do, is.
另一件我們想做的事
Set usersInTheMiddleOfTypeingANumber to false.
設置 usersInTheMiddleOfTypeingANumber 為 false
Because we might have been typing a number, but
因為我們可能已經輸入了一個數字
as soon as we hit enter, we're putting it on the stack.
但是，只要我們單擊 enter 鍵，我們將把數字放入棧中
Next time we type a digit,
接下來我們再輸入一個數字
we're going to be starting a new number.
我們將輸入一個新的數字
All right, so we'll call that user in
好了，那麼我們
the middle of typing falls there.
把它設置為 false 就好了
Now, let's go ahead and, and actually run this and
現在，讓我們繼續，運行這個
see how this is working.
看看它是怎麼工作的
Because there's going to be a little problem here.
因為這裡有個小問題
So, run this.
那麼，先運行一下
Alright, so let's try eight, enter.
好了，讓我們試一下輸入 8，然後回車
Oh.Oh
What's that? Oh, my god.
那是什麼？
Six, enter.
6，然後回車
Well it's, it's kind of working because after we
好吧，它能運行，但是我們
press enter the user is in the middle of typing numbers.
所按的回車也一起出現在數字裡面了
Starts over.
重新開始
So that's good, but I had no intention for
所以這是好的，但是我並不想
this to be showing up on the end of my display.
讓這個在最後顯示出來
This little enter.
這個 enter
What the heck is that doing on there?
到底發生了什麼？
Why is that happening?
為什麼會發生這樣的事
Let's take a look here.
讓我們看看這裡
The problem here, has to do with the messages being sent.
問題出在這裡，在發消息之前
So, when we wire this up, that's good.
那麼，當我們連接好了
We got enter.
我們已經有 enter 鍵了
The problem is that button also sends a appendDigit.
問題是那個按鈕還傳遞 appendDigit 消息
That's because we copied and pasted this three, remember?
那是因為我們複製粘貼的 3 的按鈕，記得麼？
And the three sends appendDigit, until we copy and
而 3 按鈕還傳遞了 appendDigit，直到我們複製
paste it.
粘貼了它
Now, this one sends, sends appendDigit.
現在 ，這個按鈕發送了 appendDigit
So this is both.
而且這個也是
Okay, sending two.
傳遞了兩次
Now, that's a common mistake to make.
這是一個很常見的錯誤
You know, you only think about that when you copy and
你們知道麼，你們不會去想這些當你們複製
paste it.
粘貼它
And how do we fix this?
那麼我們如何來修復這個問題？
Well if you right click, so
好了，如果你們右擊一下
I'm going to right click on this button.
我將右鍵一下這個按鈕
You'll get this window that comes up.
你們將會看到這個窗口
And it shows you all the connections from this
然後你們可以看到所有的連接
UI element to your code.
UI 元素到你們的代碼
And you can see here both appendage and
你們可以看到這裡都連接
enter are connected.
enter 鍵
The great thing is I can just click this little X right here
最棒的事我可以點擊這裡的 X 按鈕
and it'll take this connection away.
然後這個連接就被取消了
So now I only have enter.
那麼，現在我們只有 enter 鍵的連接了
So now if I go back here.
那麼現在我們再回到之前的地方
See it's,
看這裡
it's not sending appendDigit, it is sending enter.
它將不再發送 appendDigit，它只發送 enter
And you can do this right clicking for anything.
你們可以右鍵操作任何你們想做的
Like we need to do it for our label up here.
就像我們連接 label 一樣
See there's the display connection we have right here.
看到沒，這裡顯示了我們的連接
So don't forget right click to disconnect things.
不要忘記右鍵去除連接
Now if you forget about this and you don't do it.
現在，如果你們忘記這個，你們不要去操作它
Or maybe you have it wired to some thing that you change.
否則你們會連接一些你們修改的東西
For example, if we have accidentally put an argument
比如，我們需要傳遞一個參數
here to enter, if we had made it do descending button trick,
對於 enter 鍵來說，如果我們已經做過了
kind of like this.
像這樣的
You can't just say, oh okay.
你們不能說好的
I'll fix that.
我將會修復它
I'll just delete that
我將會刪除它的
Because that would not work because,
因為它將會不工作
enter with an argument is actually a different
因為帶有參數的 enter 鍵
message than enter with no argument.
對於沒參數的 enter 鍵來說發送的是不同的消息
And so, if you just deleted that when you were running
如果你們在運行的時候刪除了這些
your program it would crash and
你的應用將會崩潰
it would say, couldn't send message enter colon.
它會說，不能發送消息 enter:
When you touch this button cause enter colon means enter
當你點擊 enter 鍵的時候
with an argument, only for the purpose of this tour It doe-,
enter: 代表有參數，但是代碼中看不到
we don't see enter colon in our code.
enter: 參數
That's just something that's, this story board here.
這就是 Story board 中發生的一些事
So if that happens, you need to right click on here and
那麼如果這個發生了，你需要點擊這裡
disconnect the enter colon, that happened in there and
去除連接，然後再重新
then you just recontrol drag.
拖拽連接
When you recontrol drag it's nice it will.
當你重新連接好，它會變正常了
Kind of let you try to grab onto something, so
這裡好像讓你抓住什麼東西一樣
its easy to reconnect.
它很容易重新連接
OKay
All right, so now we want to actually implement enter here.
好了，那麼現在我們在這裡實現這個方法
We want to enter the guts of it.
我們開始著手實現它的內部
And so we are going to need another property here which is
我們需要在這定義另一個屬性
going to be that
它將是用
internal stack that these numbers are going to go on.
一個內部的棧去存儲這些數字
And so that's gonna be a var just like
所以它會是一個變量，就像
this var up here that we've created and
我們剛創建的這個變量
I'm call it operand stack that's a good name for it.
我叫它 operandStack，不錯的名字
And it's gonna have a type,
它會有一個類型
it's type is going to be an array and
它的類型是數組
just like in other languages like Java when you specify,
就像在其他語言中，比如說 Java
when you create an array type you have to specify.
當你創建一個數組，你必須指明它的類型
What kind of thing is in the array.
表明數組裡面存儲的是什麼
And so, I'm gonna put doubles in my array.
因此，我打算在裡面存放 double 元素
And that's, even though you might say, well we can't
嗯 也許你會說，好吧我們並不能
enter doubles, because these are all integers, basically.
輸入 double，因為這裡大都是些整數
But if I were to say, 3 enter 6 divide, I get .5.
但是假如我說，輸入 3 除以 6，我會得到 0.5
So than a double would appear.
這樣就出現了一個 double 的結果
So that's why I'm going to use double.
這就是我為什麼要使用 double 的原因
Now, you can see that we've got this error up here again.
現在，你們可以看到這裡又彈出了這個錯誤
It says stored property operandStack does not
上面說 「存儲的 property operandStack 並沒有
have initial value.
一個初始值」
So we have to give this an initial value.
所以我們得賦給它初始值
So I'm going to give this an initial value of
我準備把初始值賦為
an empty array.
一個空的數組
So now you're seeing for the first time how you actually.
現在你們第一次看到如何
Create an instance of a class or of a data type.
創建一個類或者數據類型的實例
And you do that just by specifying the type and
你只需要在這指明類型
then use parenthesis.
然後加上圓括號
Now, we're not,
現在，我們沒有
again we haven't talked about initializers.
我們還沒有討論過初始化方法（initializer）
A class or
一個類或者
a data structure can have multiple initializers.
一種數據類型可以有許多初始化方法
Some of them might have arguments in here.
其中的一些可能會需要參數
But most, if it's possible they'll allow you to
但大多數情況，如果允許，你都可以
create them with no arguments and in a case on
利用沒有參數的初始化方法來創建對象
array，it's very obvious what to do.
對於這裡的數組，很明顯
No arguments just creates an empty array right,
不需要參數，只要創建一個空的數組
with no elements in it.
數組內部不需要任何的元素
Now, one thing I want to talk about is this right here.
現在，我想說一下這裡的這個東西（第一個 Array）
This type, you know?
這個東西，你們知道嗎
It's kind of annoying that we have to type this and
你會覺得很煩，如果在前面定義了類型
then we have to type it right again.
然後在後面又得定義一遍
And the answer is, we don't have to do that,
而事實上，我們並不需要這麼做
because in swift, swift is very strongly typed.
因為 Swift 是強類型語言
You know there's all the variables, but
所有的變量
the properties are strongly typed.
屬性都是強類型的
But they, there's also a lot of type inference.
而且 Swift 可以做很多的類型推斷
So swift can infer.
類型推斷
This type in the exact same way that digit had no type and
比如說這裡的 digit 並沒有聲明類型
it inferred it from here.
但它可以從後面的語句中推斷出來
OperandStack, we don't have to specify they type, and
operandStack，我們並不需要指明它的類型，因為
it can infer it from here.
可以從這裡的初始化方法中推斷出來
And if we option click on operandStack you'll see that
如果我們按住 option 點擊 operandStack，你會看到
indeed, it's figured out that that's an array of double.
它確實可以辨識出這是一個 double 類型的數組
And in fact,
事實上
putting the type in here is considered bad form.
在這裡指明類型被認為是不好的書寫形式
If it can be inferred, you should let it infer, so,
如果可以推斷出類型，你就應該讓它（編譯器）自己去推斷，所以
if we didn't have this bool up here we shouldn't that either,
拿這裡的 Bool 來說，我們其實不需要聲明類型
because, false, and true are, can only be bool values so,
因為 false 和 true 只可能是 Bool 類型的
we're gonna take that off as well.
所以我們也可以把它去掉
Okay, so, now, our operand
好了，那麼現在，我們這裡有操作符棧
stack right here what do we wanna do with it?
我們打算把怎麼處理它呢？
Well, when we press enter, we just want to append.
嗯，我們按下回車，然後我們想要 append
So, append.
所以，append
This is actually the first time we're sending an actual
事實上這是我們第一次發送一條
message to an object looks just like when we
消息給一個對象，但是這種寫法就像
accessed a property.
獲取了一個屬性一樣
The dot and it's just the name of the method that we're
輸入點號，然後就出現了我們想要在這個數組上
trying to invoke in our arrays.
調用的方法名字
Just an array, an array method right here called a append.
這是一個叫做 append 的數組方法
I think you see the arguments as newElement: T.
我想你們看到了這個參數 —— newElement: T
This : T means it has to be of this type.
這個 : T 意味著它必須是這個類型
Type of things in the array so this has to be a double.
這個數組裡面東西的類型，所以它必須是一個 double
So that's kind of a problem, cuz really what I want to
這也是一個問題，因為事實上我想要在
append onto my stack is what's up here in this display text.
我的棧上附加的是，這裡 display.text 的內容
And, you know, I'd like to say something along the lines
然後在這行輸入
of display.text.
display.text
Okay? But what type is this?
好吧，它的類型是什麼呢？
I can type display.text.（type of display.text？？）
display.text 的類型
Now that's not String.
它不是 String
That is an optional.
它是一個 optional String
Remember that display.text is an optional.
記住這裡的 display.text 是一個 optional String
So we can unwrap it even though
所以我們可以把它拆包，但
that's not gonna solve the problem.
這並不能解決問題
This is still a String and
這仍是一個 String
you're still seeing an error here.
你們還是可以看到這裡有一個錯誤
This saying 'String' is not convertible to double [COUGH].
上面寫著 「String 不可以轉化為 Double」
Because we're supposed to be putting doubles in
因為我們本應把 Double 放入
this array putting Strings.
這個數組而不是 String
So, we have a problem here.
所以，我們在這有個問題
We have somehow to convert this String into a double so
我們得用某種方式把 String 轉化成 Double 以便
we can put it on this stack.
我們把它放入棧中
I'm gonna use this opportunity.
我要借用這個機會，
Just show you another feature which we
向你們展示另一個特性，我們
call Computed Properties.
稱之為計算型屬性（Computed Properties）
So I'm gonna create another property display value and
所以我要在這裡創建另一個屬性 displayValue,
it's gonna be a Double.
它是一個 Double
And what I want this to be equal to is, I always want it
然後我想讓它等於，我想讓它
to be whatever's in this display converted to a double.
等於這裡的顯示轉化成 Double 的值
Okay? And I want to
好了，然後我想
be able to set it or get it so
有辦法對它進行設值以及取值，以便
I'm gonna be able to get the value of this double.
我能夠取到這個 Double 的值
I just want to be able to set it as a double and
我想把它設值成一個 Double 然後
have it turn into text.
把它轉化成文本
Well, that kind of
好吧，這種類型的
property really is tied to some data somewhere else.
屬性實際上是與其他地方的某些數據綁定的
So, I don't ever want to set it equal to some initial value
所以，我不想把它設成某個初始值
or something.
還是其他的什麼
Really, I want it to always be calculated and we can do that.
我想讓它總是由計算得到的，而我們在 Swift 里可以做到
Instead of saying equals something,
與其輸入 「這個變量等於什麼什麼」
you just put curly braces after.
你只需要在後面輸入，花括號
And you say, get, and we say, set.
然後寫下 get ，再寫 set
Okay?
就好了
And inside here we are gonna compute the value of this.
然後在這裡面，我們要對它的值進行計算了
Which is we are gonna convert this display text
這將會把這裡的 display.text 轉化成
to a double and then inside here, we are, someone said,
Double，然後在這裡，我們要，要讓
display value equal something and we are going to
displayValue 等於什麼，我們要做的是
somehow compute, not really compute it, but.
想辦法能夠計算它，並不是真正計算某一個特定的值，而是
We're gonna de, decide, what code we need to put that
我們要決定我們需要什麼樣的代碼能夠
number that they tried to set the display value to in here.
決定 displayValue 在這裡被設成什麼值
'Kay, so let's do the set side first.
好吧，那麼讓我們先來寫 set 方法
It's actually a little simpler.
這其實會簡單一些
Inside this set,
在 set 方法里
there's a magic variable called new value.
會有一個叫作 newValue 的變量
It doesn't, it's not purple for some reason, but.
因為某些原因，它的高亮並不是顯示為紫色的
New value in this, this is the new value.
這裡的 newValue 就是將要被設置的那個值
So if someone says somewhere in our code,
如果說某些人在我們的代碼里
display value equals five,
讓 displayValue 的值等於 5
this new value will have the five.
那這個 newValue 就會是 5
And so all I really wanna do
我所想做的
here is say display text equals the new value.
就是在這，讓 display.text 等於 newValue
But again, of course this is an optional String.
但同樣的問題，這是個 optional String
You can't set it to a double because displayValue equals
你不能把它設成一個 Double，因為 displayValue 等於
five, this new values going to be a double.
5，這個 newValue 將會是一個 Double
But we know how to convert something to a String by
但是我們知道如何把它轉化成 String，只需要寫上
using backlash parenthesis.
反斜線，圓括號
And this is the same thing we did when we
這其實和我們
printed out [COUGH] our digit up here.
之前輸出的 digit 的過程是一樣的
We just use the back slash parenthesis.
我們只需要寫上反斜線和圓括號
It tries to convert this thing inside here,
它會試著在這裡轉化這個東西
which is a double into a String of doubles.
把一個 Double 轉化成 String
You know how to do that themselves.
你知道該怎麼做了
And so bingo, we've got our display text and
沒錯 我們有了自己的 display.text
that's all that necessary.
這就夠了
also, every time someone sets this displayValue and then we're
而且，每次有人設 displayValue 的值時
clearly not in the middle of typing a number anymore.
很明顯，我們知道，此時我們不在是在輸入數字的狀態了
[INAUDIBLE] Say that.
把這個狀態設置成 false
[INAUDIBLE] All right, what about the getting?
好吧，那關於取值呢？
Now in the getting all we have to do is
在取值方法中，我們所要做的就是
return this display value.
返回 displayValue
So it's do something to calculate what this
所以這裡需要做的就是計算
display value is here.
這裡的 displayValue
And then return it.
然後返回它
Now this one I'm not gonna take time to go
這次我不會花時間去
through the details here.
詳細說明細節
And actually I've made it an extra credit item that you can
實際上我把它算作一個給你們去做的額外加分項
do, which requires you to figure out
需要你們利用文檔，去搞清楚我在這寫的代碼
what I'm gonna type here using the documentation.
是什麼意思
But I'm not going to explain it here.
但現在我不想給出代碼的解釋
I'm gonna use a class that's in this number formatter.
這裡，我要在使用一個叫作 NumberFormatter 的類
I'm actually gonna create one and
我先創建一個實例，然後
I'm gonna use a method on it called number from String.
使用它的 numberFromString 方法
And I'm gonna give it this String which is
然後我會把這個字符串傳給它，
the display values text, unwrapped of course.
這個字符串也就是 display.text，當然得拆包
The result is acting optional so I'm gonna unwrap that.
它的返回值是一個 optional String，所以我繼續要把它拆包
And then I'm gonna get the double value of the thing I
然後我再得到它返回的 Double 值
get back [COUGH].
Number gives me this kind of generic number so
Number 給了我這種泛型的數字，所以
I am gonna take it and turn it into a double.
我把它轉化成一個 Double
So there we go.
好了
So you can go the next spread and
你們可以繼續下一步了
look at that later if you want.
如果你想的話，以後再考慮它
But surprising to say we
高興的是，我們
now have a property display value that when we set it and
現在有了一個 displayValue 的屬性，當我們設值和取值時
get it, it's gonna be setting and getting.
我們調用了自定義的 set 和 get 方法
It has a String here, so that is really convenient.
UILabel 這裡是一個字符串，所以也挺方便的
Especially for
尤其是這裡
right here, where we wanna say display value.
其實我們想傳入的是 displayValue
'Kay?
明白了嗎？
So let's see the double.
讓我們回頭檢查一下，Double
No problem.
沒錯
We're pinning that onto operandStack.
我們把它附到 operandStack 上了，而 operandStack 里的元素也是 Double 的
So let's print in our operandStack here.
接下來，讓我們把 operandStack 在這打印出來
Just so, I mean we can do the same thing here, operandStack.
就像這樣，一樣的方式，\(operandStack)
Okay?
沒問題吧？
And this worked because operandStack is an array, and
這種方式可行是因為 operandStack 是一個數組
arrays know how to turn themselves into Strings.
數組知道如何把它們自身轉化成字符串
You'll see how they do that in the console in a moment here.
你一會兒就會在控制台輸出里看到它們是怎麼做到的了
So let's go ahead and
所以，我們繼續
see if our application is actually putting things on
來看看我們的應用是否真的正確地能夠把東西放到
our stack properly here.
我們的棧里
[NOISE] All right.
好的
Let's try here.
我們嘗試著在這裡
Let's try 56 enter.
在這裡輸入 56
And look, operandStack equals 56 doing good.
看，operandStack 是等於 56，運行正常
Seven enter.
輸入 7
All right, 56.0 and 7.0.
好的，56.0 和 7.0
So, you can see that arrays turn themselves into Strings
所以你們看到了數組是如何把自身轉化成字符串的
by doing open square bracket and then they turn each of
在這個方括號里，它們把自身的每個
their elements into Strings and separated by commas.
元素轉化成字符串並以逗號分隔
Now this is good.
這個就搞定了
So we got our operand, operandStack building here.
我們這的 operandStack 就創建好了
So all we need to do is have some times, and plus, and
接下來我們現在需要做的就是要有乘法，加法和
minus buttons, etc.
減法之類的按鈕
I'm gonna put them right here.
我準備把它們放在這個位置
That will operate on these items uh, on the stack.
它在在這些項上進行運算，準確的說是在棧上
So, if I pressed plus right now,
所以，如果我現在按下加
it would pull the seven and the eight off the stack.
它就會把 7 和 8 從棧中取出來（pop）
Add them together, it would be 15.
把他們相加，得到 15
Show that 15 here, and
然後在這裡顯示 15
it actually will put the 15 back on the stack.
實際上，15 會被放回到棧里（push）
So then, we'd have 56 and 15 on our stack.
然後，我們的棧里就有了 56 和 15
Then we could, maybe.
接著我們就可以
Plus those together and we wanted by it plus again.
再運行一次加法，把它們加到一起
All right?
沒錯吧？
[COUGH] Okay.
好的
So how are we gonna do that?
所以我們應該怎麼做呢？
Well, we would make our buttons here.
嗯，我們將把這些運算符的按鈕放在這個位置
And I'm gonna make the buttons again by copying and
我通過複製粘貼數字按鈕來
pasting a digit button.
創建這些個運算符按鈕
But this time I know about that problem,
但是這次我已經知道會出現哪個問題了
so right off the bat I'm gonna right click on it.
所以我馬上就右鍵點擊剛才粘貼的按鈕
And disconnect appendDigit: it.
然後取消和 appendDigit 方法的關聯
Okay? So
好的，那麼
now this button sends no messages, yet anyway.
現在，這個按鈕就不會發送任何消息了
And then we could put a type on here.
然後我們要在這上面設置一個運算符
So here I'm gonna have my all my operations buttons use
這裡我要讓所有的運算符按鈕都使用
mathematical symbols so if we go down here to math symbols.
數學符號，而不是編程中的那些運算符號，所以我們看這裡的 Math Symbols
See there's a bunch of math symbols here.
看這裡有好多數學符號
So let's do times, right here,
現在，我們來給乘法設置符號
first, we'll put times right there, and we can wire it up.
首先，把乘法放到這，然後我們可以把它與代碼鏈接在一起
I'm just gonna hold that Ctrl and drag out here.
按住 Ctrl 然後拖動這裡來
We're gonna call this action method.
我們把這個 Action 稱作
Operate.
operate 方法
And because I'm gonna have multiple operation buttons and
因為會有許多運算按鈕，所以
they're all going to send operate.
他們都會發送 operate 消息
Just like I did with append digit,
就像數字按鈕和 appendDigit 方法鏈接在一起一樣
I am going to use the sender.
我要使用這個 sender
So I'm gonna be very careful to change this any
所以我得仔細地
object to be button.
把 Sender 的類型從 AnyObject 改成 UIButton
Do not forget that.
不要忘記這點
'Kay, so action, we are gonna have it sender.
Sender 類型
UIButton.
為 UIButton
Call it operate.
Action 名字為 operate
There it is.
就是這些設置了
That's method doing operate.
這就是做操作符運算的方法
We can copy and paste this button now, right?
我們現在可以複製粘貼這個按鈕了
We got this one, so
我們用乘法的這個
let's copy and paste and make some more of these.
複製粘貼，然後重復，重復
We'll start out with four of them, let's say.
我們先粘貼出 4 個運算符
'Kay?
Let's get back our special characters here.
我們回到特殊符號這裡
[COUGH] All right, so let's make this one be divide.
我們來把第二個設置為除法
Let's make this one plus.
第三個，加法
And this one be minus.
最後一個，減法
All right.
好了
So we've got these buttons [COUGH].
操作符按鈕就完成了
And they're all sending, if we look at this here,
它們都會發送，如果我們看這裡
they're all sending operate.
它們都會發送 operate 消息
Luckily, they're not sending anything except operate, so
幸運的是它們並不會發送運算之外的東西
that's good.
這樣就好
And when they send operate, we're gonna figure out
當它們發送同樣的 operate 消息的時候，我們要搞清楚
which one is sending it by the same exact way we did above.
發送消息的對象是哪一個
We're gonna say what is the sender's current title?
也就是說，Sender 的 currentTitle 是什麼？
We're gonna unwrap it.
我們要把它拆包
So operation here is gonna be a String.
這裡的 operation 是一個 String
And it's going to tell us the title of the buttons so
它會告訴我們按鈕的 title，所以
we know which one to use there.
我們就知道了該怎麼處理
Now I'm gonna show you a control flow operator here in
現在我要給你們展示 Swift 中的控制流符號
Swift that's very powerful, much more powerful than
它非常強大，比其他語言中的強大多了
this operator is in other languages.
And also very, very important to swift.
而且對 Swift 語言自身來說是很重要的
I'm only gonna show you the simplest usage of it here, but
這裡我只會向你們展示控制流符號最簡單的用法
you're gonna see on Monday's demonstration and
你們會在週一的展示和
later in the quarter how important this operator is.
接下來的學習中感受到它的強大之處
But, it's switch, okay, and
switch
switch looks like switch in other languages, like C.
它和其他語言中的 switch 看起來很像，比如說 C
You switch on something.
你在某個變量上使用 switch
In this case I'm gonna switch on this String.
在這裡，我會在這個字符串上 switch
This is the String.
字符串 operation
Then you just specify the case of each thing.
然後你指明所有 case 情況
So for example here I have a case.
舉例來說，有一個 case
Let's do the multiply.
進行乘法
Okay, so we've got multiply case right here.
那我們就在這裡創建一個乘法 case
And then we just put the code that we want here
接著我們只需把做乘法的代碼
for multiply.
放到這裡
And we'd do that for all the other cases here.
接著對其他的操作符 case 也這麼做
So let's copy and paste.
複製粘貼一下
And we'll do this be our divide case.
這個是除法 case
And we'll have this be our plus case and
這個是加法 case
we'll have this be our,
在這裡是減法 case
make sure we're doing the same here, plus case.
我們在複製粘貼減法 case 的時候
Again, you've got to be a little careful here.
你需要仔細一點
You know, this minus is slightly different from this
因為左邊的減號符號和
minus which might be slightly different than the minus
右邊的減號符號有輕微的不同
you type with the keyboard.
右邊的減號符號是你從鍵盤上輸入的那種
So, when you're putting the symbols here,
所以，當你們在這放置符號的時候
you wanna use exactly the same symbols here in your case.
你們要確保代碼中的和 Storyboard 中使用的是同一個
Now, one thing about switch on Swift though is it
關於 Swift 中的 switch，要注意的一件事就是
absolutely requires that you have every case covered.
你必須確保覆蓋所有情況（case）
Now since this is a String, obviously can't have case of
由於這是一個字符串，你顯然不可能
every single String in the universe.
窮舉每一種情況
That is almost infinite, but luckily there,
通常是無限多的，但是很幸運的是
you can take defaults and just break out of the switch.
可以在 default 後，使用 break 來跳出 switch
That means if it's not one of these cases by default just
也就意味著，如果不是 default 之前列舉的那些情況
break out of the switch.
就會跳出 switch
You could put code here as well,
這不是說代碼不能放在 default 中
but breaking out of it is what we wanna do in our case.
只是在這裡，我們想要從 switch 中 break 而已
now, in here, we're just going to put the code for multiply.
現在，在這裡，我們輸入與乘法相關的語句
So, what do we need to do for multiply?
那麼，乘法需要做些什麼?
For the moment, I'm gonna comment this out.
我會暫時將這部分注釋掉
I'm gonna use command, slash,
使用 ⌘ + / 鍵來注釋
which is a really nice feature.
這個快捷鍵的確稱得上是一個很不錯的功能
You do command slash.
按下 ⌘ + / 鍵之後
And then command slash again, to uncomment.
再次按下 ⌘ + / 鍵來取消給代碼注釋
[INAUDIBLE] real quick cuz I just wanna focus on times.
這裡我想專注於乘法操作的代碼
Now any time I press any operator,
任何時候，點擊任何操作符
I probably wanna give the user an automatic enter.
我希望自動給用戶按下 enter 按鈕
That's so that six enter, three enter,
也就是 6，enter，3，enter
times is the same as six enter three times.
乘法，等價於 6 乘以 3
Okay, so six enter three times is gonna do an automatic enter
這裡，6，enter，3，乘法會自動在
on that three.
在 3 之後輸入一個 enter
Cuz obviously, I intend to have six and
顯然在這種情況下，我想讓 6 和
three be multiplied in that case.
3 相乘
So for all of these operations, I going to say,
所以，對於所有的操作符的 Action
if the users in the middle of typing a number.
如果用戶正在輸入一個數字（userIsInTheMiddleOfTypingANumber 為 true）
Then hit enter for me, right here.
那麼，我要自動幫用戶輸入一個 enter，即調用 enter()
Okay, so [COUGH] what do we need to do in
接下來，我們
this specific case of times?
需要乘法在這裡做什麼？
Well, really we just want to set our display value.
我們需要在這裡對 displayValue 設值
Remember we have our nice display value down here.
還記得嗎？我們自定義了 displayValue 的取值和設值方法
And we can do setting as well as getting.
取值和設值方法
So I set that display value.
因此，我在這裡需要做的是
Up here.
設值
Equal to multiplying the top two things on this stack.
displayValue 等於將棧頂的兩個數相乘
So I can actually remove something off our stack.
因此，我可以從棧里移除一些元素
We're representing our stack as an array.
我們可以使用一個數組代表棧結構
Of course, they are stacked as an array.
而且，這裡確實是使用了一個數組來表示棧結構
And so a stack is something you push things on,
棧是一種數據結構，你可以壓入元素到棧里
you pop things off.
也可以從棧里彈出元素
And with an array, we're just gonna add something there at
用數組實現的話，我們只需要
the end to push something on, and
在數組的末尾添加一個元素，來模擬元素的入棧操作
that will just remove it from the end to pop it off.
在數組的末尾移除一個元素，來模擬元素的出棧操作
So there's a nice.
沒問題吧？
All right. This is an array, right?
好的，這是一個數組
Operand stacks.
數組名稱是 operandStack
There's a nice method called remove last.
有個方法叫 removeLast()
And if we option click on remove last, you'll see here
如果在 removeLast 方法上按住 option 鍵並單擊
that it removes an element from the end of the array.
可以看到說明：從數組的末尾移除一個元素
Now, it does require a count greater than zero.
這個方法需要數組的元素個數大於零
So if our array were empty this would crash our program.
如果數組是空的話，移除元素會導致程序崩潰
So let's put a little protective thing here.
所以，在這裡做一些保護性的措施.
If the operand stacks.
如果 operandStack
There's a nice property here called Count on that.
operandStack 變量有一個屬性叫做 count
It is greater or
如果它大於或者
equal to two actually because multiply takes two operand so
等於 2，因為乘法需要 2 個操作數
there better two things on this stack.
所以棧中至少需要有 2 個元素
Then we can do this and so
那麼我們可以把這取出來的棧頂元素
we're gonna multiply that by and remove the next one.
相乘上第二次調用 removeLast() 所取出來的棧頂元素
Okay?
明白了嗎？
So here we got-
這樣的話
We're just taking the last two things off of this stack by
我們從棧中移除最頂上的兩個元素
removing them from the end of the array and
通過從數組中移除最後的元素（removeLast 方法）
just assigning it to display value.
將運算結果賦值給 displayValue 變量
And we probably also want to do an enter here,
接著，我們希望在這裡輸入一個 enter()
because [COUGH] if I go six enter three times,
如果用戶按下了 6，enter，3，乘
well then I want to be able to say then nine plus and
然後接著，用戶按下了 9，加
have it add onto the six times three.
這代表著在原來運算的結果上加 9
So we want an automatic enter here, as well.
所以，這裡需要一個自動點擊 enter 的操作
Okay?
明白了嗎？
So, that's pretty much all we need to do here.
這大概就是我們所有需要在這裡做的了
Let's go ahead and run this, see how this works.
讓我們運行這個應用，看看它是否正常工作
And so, six enter, or three enter, six enter.
我們嘗試輸入 3，enter，6，enter
Now we've got them both on the stack.
我們可以從控制台看到它們已經在棧上了
Times and you can see we put our 18 here.
然後我讓它們相乘，可以看到結果是 18
It also put it back on the stack and
18 這個結果也被放入了棧中
we can say five times.
我們再輸入 5，乘
That put a five on the stack and
這個操作將 5 放入棧中,
then multiplied them, took it off.
將它們兩個從棧中移除並相乘，返回結果
So that's working nicely.
程序正常運行
[COUGH] Now what about our-
現在
Other buttons, here.
我們的其他的運算符按鈕
We gonna make those work.
我們想要讓它們正常工作
Let's do that.
讓我們繼續完成
Now, they do a very similar thing, here.
其他的運算符功能和乘法的功能是十分相似的
So, one temptation would be to just copy here.
所以，我們複製乘法的這部分代碼
Let's uncomment these out.
先取消這部分的注釋
And then just paste it, repeatedly.
然後重復粘貼
So, put it there.
放到這些位置
There, there and then just changes times in here.
只需要修改這裡的乘號
D note to plus for example on this one.
把這個換成個加號
But his is pretty messy code, look at all this
但是，這樣的代碼看起來很亂
incredible amount of duplicating code, in here.
這裡有大量的重復的代碼
We really probably wouldn't to write our code like this.
我們不希望代碼寫成這樣子
People would think we were terrible programmers I
如果寫成這樣，別人會認為我們是很糟糕的程序員
think if we did that.
Really what would be nice is if we had some,
什麼樣的代碼看起來會不錯呢？
could write some kind of function.
那就是如果我們可以把這些重復的代碼寫成函數
Maybe we could call it perform operation or
然後給函數起名為 perfomOperation
something like that.
或者類似意思的名字
And if the argument to that function.
至於函數的參數
Remember that arguments have names.
需要注意的是，函數參數也是有名字的
Here's the name.
這就是參數的名字
And then we have the type.
然後是參數的類型
The argument were something which basically was this
這裡的參數是
little operation in here, or
這裡的運算操作符
some sort of function that would do this operation.
或者是能夠完成運算操作符操作的函數
So if this could be some sort of function that
如果可以把這些重復代碼寫成函數的話
would be cool.
看起來就很棒了
Then, maybe we could.
接下來
I take this code out of here, put it in here.
將這段代碼移動到這個位置
Let's call it perform not pre-form, perform operation.
並起名為 performOperation
[LAUGH] Put it in here and
放到這裡
instead of doing, you know, multiply here.
這裡注意，我們把乘號改掉
Let's go ahead and we can do this operation some how.
用其他的方式來進行運算
I guess, well maybe operation,
可能是某個叫 operation 函數
call it like a function with two arguments here.
接受兩個參數
Okay. That would be
好了，這樣看起來很不錯了
cool because we'd be sharing, you know, this check.
因為我們復用了這段代碼，復用了這個判讀
We'd be sharing this enter.
復用了這 enter 方法
[COUGH] We'd be sharing the removal of the operator.
復用了從棧中彈出兩個元素的方法
We'd be sharing the same display value.
復用了 displayValue 變量
We'd be kind of sharing a lot of code here and
通過這樣，復用了大段的代碼
then up here if we could just do something like,
至於在上面的 case 中國年，我們只需要像這樣
perform operation, and, somehow, specify,
調用函數 performOperation，並且
multiply, as the operation we wanted to do here.
指定函數參數 multiply
And then we wouldn't need all this stuff here, right?
原來的那一大段代碼就都不需要了，明白了嗎？
So this is gonna be cool.
看起來很不錯
Now, can we do this?
有人會質疑，我們可以這樣做嗎？
Well, yes, the answer is we can.
答案是當然可以
And so, types, functions.
參數類型，函數
Can be types in Swift, just like any other type.
函數在 Swift 里可以被當做一種類型，就像 Swfit 中其他的類型一樣
So, you know, we have a double here, oops, double.
你知道，這裡需要一個 Double 類型的參數
That's a type.
就是這個類型
You can also have a function type.
當然也可以有一個函數類型的參數
So how do you specify a function type?
那麼，怎麼指定一個函數類型呢？
Well multiple I or
無論是 multiple
whatever function I'm about to perform here.
或者是任何其他我想要在這裡執行的函數
This is a function that takes two doubles as arguments.
這樣的函數需要兩個 Double 類型的參數
And it returns a double.
並且，它的返回值類型也是一個 Double 類型
So, I can just say, I want operation to be
所以我在這裡輸入
a function that takes two doubles and returns a double.
我想要 operation 是一個函數，帶兩個 Double 類型參數，返回 Double 類型
I can express that right here.
這就是我要表達的
This is a type, the type of this.
這就是函數類型的定義
Argument right here that you can click on and say yeah
在函數的名稱上按住 option 單擊
that type is double takes two doubles and returns a double.
你可以看到信息：2 個 Double 類型的參數，1 個 Double 類型的返回值
So, just simple as that.
就是這麼簡單
So all we need now is a function here
我們目前已知的就是，這裡有一個函數
called multiply that takes two doubles and
這個函數名稱為 multiply，帶 2 個 Double 類型的參數
returns a double and does multiplication.
返回 1 個 Double 類型的返回值，函數功能是完成乘法操作
So we could go down here and say okay multiply and
接下來我們在下面輸入 multiply 函數的代碼
you'll have op1 which is double and op2.
第一個參數 op1，Double 類型，第二個參數 op2
[COUGH] A double and it returned the double.
Double 類型，返回一個 Double 類型
And it's just return one times out two.
返回值是 op1 乘以 op2 的結果
Okay?
對嗎？
And that worked great.
一切都很好
Back out again so we can see if this actually works.
回到上面，看它是否真的可以正常運行
But there's no errors here.
沒有任何錯誤
Right? It seems to work.
對麼？看起來很正常
Multiply seems to be a function to take the $2 and
multiply 就是一個接受兩個參數，返回一個 Double 這樣的函數
turns it double.
And that's what this argument here is and
這就是 performOperation 的參數
I'm passing it along.
我將 multiply 傳入
It should all work so let's give it a try.
這一切都沒有問題，所以應該是可行的，那麼我們來試一下吧
So here we go as six enter.
輸入 6，enter
54 times and sure enough it's working it.
54，乘以，輸出結果是 324.0，沒問題
It's doing that multiplication.
完成了乘法操作，我們可以在控制台輸出里看到
Works great and so what about all of our other cases here?
乘法做的不錯，其他的 case 情況呢？
Well we would just need to take this same.
只需要也像 multiply 這樣做
Piece of code right here and put it for all of them.
我們在所有的 case 情況下粘貼 performOperation(multiply)
And of course we need a divide method, so we have to
當然了，我們需要除法函數
come down here, and copy and paste that, and make divide.
所以把這裡 multiply 改名為 divide，同時，然後複製 multiply 的實現並在它的下面粘貼更名為 divide
Oh wait a second,
稍等
this is starting to be just as bad as I had before.
這又像之前看起來的那樣糟糕了
Having to make all these extra functions, multiply and
需要這些額外的函數：乘法
divide and all that.
除法，等等
Well [COUGH] it turns out it's so
事情上
common to pass functions as arguments in Swift, that it
在 Swift 中，將函數作為參數傳遞是很常見的
allows you to put a function like multiply right in
允許你在這裡傳遞一個，例如 multiply 的函數
here without having to create a separate function like this.
而不需要單獨創建一個函數
And all you do is you just pick it up.
所有你需要做的是就是選中函數的這塊部分
So I'm just going to cut that from down here and
從這裡剪切
I'm going to paste it right in here.
粘貼到上面這裡來
The only thing you have to change syntactically when you
唯一需要在語法上做的改變的就是
do that is this curly brace, okay.
這裡左側的花括號
Instead of being after the declaration of
不是之前在聲明函數的參數和返回值之後
the arguments in the return value, it needs to be before.
而是在這兩者之前
So, you move the curly brace before.
所以，你把花括號放到前面去
And then where the curly brace was,
之前這裡是小括號的位置
you gonna put in, the word in.
添加一個單詞 in
And so that allows us to just.
這裡我們稍微調整下
Come and do that again to eliminate some of our errors.
現在把這些代碼都注釋掉，不要讓程序有錯誤
And we can get rid of function multiply down here.
然後，我們就可以移除這裡的 func multiply 了
So that allows me to just put that multiplier right in here.
以上這些步驟就允許我們把乘法的實現
Right in line.
放在 case 情況的一行裡面
Right as the argument to this function.
直接給 performOperation 函數傳遞一個函數參數
And this things kind of wacky.
對於一些不瞭解的人來說
For those of you who don't know it,
這種方式看起來略古怪
user programming languages that allow this kind
但在一些編程語言中，這種寫法是允許的
of thing to happen are called closures.
這樣的情況稱之為閉包（closure）
It basically allows you to put a function right in there.
它允許你在這裡放置一個函數
And this, okay here, looks okay, I mean we can certainly
好的，這樣就看起來不錯
you know, now we can copy and paste this and put it here.
下面就可以複製，粘貼這段代碼
You know, here and
放在除法的 case 這裡
change this and put it here and change this.
然後將 divide 改成我們複製的代碼，以此類推，加法、減法也是如此
But it can even be better than this.
但是，我們可以進一步改進
So we know that Swift is really good at
我們知道 Swift 引以為傲的
something called type inference.
一個特性稱就是類型推斷
Where I can kinda figure out the type,
也就是我可以通過上下文（context）來
of something, from the context.
推斷某個東西是什麼類型的
And you can do the same thing here.
這裡你也可以這麼做
Because its looking at performOperation.
因為 Swift 的編譯器看到這裡的 performOperation
It knows you're calling perform operation.
它知道你在調用 performOperation
It knows this argument is a function that takes two
它知道這個函數的參數
doubles and returns a double.
是 2 個 Double 類型，返回值是 1 個 Double 類型的
So you really don't have to specify all the types in here.
所以在這裡，我們不需要指定參數和返回值的類型
Cuz it knows all of this.
因為編譯器知道這些事情
So you can actually get rid of all these type decorations,
所以，你可以刪除這些參數類型聲明
right here, even the return.
甚至是返回值類型也一樣可以省去
And, again, seeing no warnings, no errors.
可以看到，刪除後，沒有任何警告和錯誤
It knows that this has to be a double, and
它知道這個第一個參數必須是一個 Double 類型的
this has to be a double.
第二個參數也必須是一個 Double 類型的
Because it knows you're calling perform operation.
因為它知道你調用的是 performOperation
So it knows the argument to that is like that.
所以，它知道函數的參數是什麼類型的
Okay, and you can even make this look a little nicer.
好的，那麼我們可以對我們的代碼進行進一步的改進
We can move this all up onto one line.
把這個閉包寫在一行裡面
Really nice for readability here.
看來起更具有可讀性、更優雅
But, we can actually do even better than this,
事實上，還能有更好的寫法
because Swift knows that perform operations argument
因為 Swift 的編譯器知道這個函數
returns something, you don't need this return key if your
會返回一個 Double 的值，所以你甚至都不需要使用 return
whole is just an expression like this return key word.
如果所有的代碼只有一個返回語句
You don't need that key word because it knows this is
那就不需要 return 這個關鍵字
going to return something so
因為程序知道這裡，你要返回什麼東西
this is just an expression it's going to return it.
這樣只需要輸入一個表達式就可以了，編譯器知道這個表達式的值就是你想返回的值
But it's even better than that because a swift does
而 Swift 還有一個更棒的功能是
not force you to name these two arguments.
Swift 不強制要求你給這兩個參數命名
If you don‘t name them it will use the names $0.
如果不命名的參數的話，程序自動給參數起名為 $0
$1, and
和 $1
if you have more arguments, dollar 2, dollar 3, dollar 4.
如果你有更多的參數，將會命名為 $2，$3，$4...
So you don't even need this.
所以，函數名字也不要了
Okay?
明白了嗎？
So this is a function right here.
所以這裡的意思是，這是一個函數
It takes two doubles, dollar 0 and dollar 1, and
這個函數有兩個 Double 類型參數，名稱是 $0 和 $1
returns a double.
返回一個 Double 類型的值
Now Swift knows that they're doubles because it knows that
Swift 編譯器知道它們是 Double 類型
you're passing them to perform an operation.
因為你將它們傳遞給 performOperation
If you were passing this to some other, a function that
如果把它們傳遞給其他的函數
took different kind of function as an argument, then,
這些函數有不一樣的參數類型，那麼
you know, these types might be different but in this case it
$0 和 $1 的類型可能和上面不同
knows that's what it is and it knows that it returns once
但是在這裡，Swift 知道它們是什麼類型
it knows it's going to return what this calculation is.
也知道它們的計算結果是什麼類型的
All right.
明白了嗎？
Now one more cool syntactic thing you can do is if you
更酷的事情是
have a function like performOperation, and
如果你有一個 performOperation 這樣的函數
it has an argument which is a function like operation here,
有個像 operation 這樣的函數作為一個參數
if this argument is the last argument, okay, so
如果這個參數是最後一個參數
if I had other arguments before it, and
在它之前有別的參數
this was the argument, then you can move the function.
這是傳入的參數，那麼你就可以把這個函數
Outside the parentheses, so other arguments,
移動到括號外，至於其他的參數
if there were other arguments before, they would go in here.
如果有的話，仍舊放在括號內
But this last argument,
但是最後的參數除外，可以放在括號之後
which is this operation, gets to go outside the parentheses.
也就是這個 operation，可以放在括號外
And if there are no other arguments, if this is
如果除了最後一個參數以外，沒有其他的參數
the only argument, you can actually get rid of that.
簡單的說，只有一個參數時，你可以把括號也去掉
Okay.
明白了嗎？
So, we're cutting down to incredibly concise
因此，我們把我們乘法的代碼變得相當簡潔
language here and we can do this exact same deal,
我們再對其他的運算做同樣的事情
of course with these other form operations.
複製粘貼這個代碼
We just need to change the.
只需要改一下算數運算符
Nothing here.
這裡不需要改
This one, we be a little careful with the order of
除法需要注意的是參數的順序
operations here, we wanna do this because we
我們想把這兩個參數的位置顛倒一下
click the thing that we're dividing by on the stack last.
是因為我們希望，除數是棧中的最後一個元素
And that's the first thing that comes off the stack.
而除數是棧中最先彈出的元素
And same thing here actually,
同樣，這裡也要注意減法的參數順序
the subtraction minus dollar here.
$1 - $0
Okay, so, this is our entire operate, and
好了，這就是我們的全部的運算操作
you can see that it's incredibly concise.
你可以看到，與之前相比，這相當的簡潔
Very readable.
同時也有很高的可讀性
Times is clearly doing this function.
一眼看上去就知道這裡是在做乘法
And very extensible.
同時，這樣做保證了良好的可擴展性
If you wanna add more functions,
如果你需要添加更多的操作
we just one liners here,
只需要這裡添加一行代碼
but more these [COUGH] binary functions that have two So,
但在這裡我們就只有這麼多二元運算
let's go ahead and make sure these are all working.
讓我們運行一下，以確保我們應用沒有問題
All right.
好的
So, 6 enter 5 times, that's 30, that's good.
輸入 6，enter，5，乘法，結果是 30
How about 47 plus 77, excellent.
再來，輸入 47，加法，結果是 77，不錯
How about 2 divide.
再輸入 2，除法
38.5.
結果是 38.5
[INAUDIBLE] number there.
控制台也輸出同樣的結果
Working, you can see the stack doing all the right things.
一切都很好，控制台的輸出也沒有問題
Okay? Make sense?
沒問題吧？
Now, I'm going to do one more thing, here.
現在，我還需要做一個事情
Which is to add another operation,
就是添加另外的一個運算操作
this is going to be a slightly different operation.
它完成一個稍有不同的操作
So, I'm going to copy and
這裡，我複製一個運算符的按鈕
paste these operation buttons here.
然後粘貼到這裡
Again, I'm going to make sure they are lined up really
確保對齊
nice with as many of these blue lines as I can get.
我使用這些藍色的線來確保對齊
I'm actually going to leave these buttons here.
我打算把按鈕放在這個位置
Because you're going to need them for your homework.
因為你們等下做課後作業的時候會需要用到
But we gonna change this button right down here to be
我們將會讓這個按鈕
a different operator.
完成成為一個不同的運算
Which is going to be, square root.
它將是一個平方根運算符
Which is right here, square root operator.
就在這裡，一個平方根
All right?
有什麼問題嗎？
And, so, I'm going to go back her to do square root, and
然後我回到這裡的代碼，添加一個平方根運算
it's just another case, right.
只需要再添加一個 case 就可以搞定了
Case square root.
case "√"
And, maybe I should just be able to use the same
也許這裡我應該直接拷貝同樣的代碼
mechanism, right?
對吧？
Let's see if that works.
讓我們看看，這樣能不能行
Place that in there.
把它們放在這
And instead of this bracket here, let's use the built in
把花括號里的內容刪掉，用一個
function in Swift to do square root called sqrt.
Swift 里內置的平方根運算函數，叫做 sqrt
And a dollar there.
還有一個 $0
Looks good.
看起來不錯
And then we're ready to go.
好的，我們準備運行我們的應用
Let's just work, call it, what's going on here.
稍等，這裡好像有什麼問題
They have some sort of error, what's the problem.
好像是某種錯誤，是什麼問題呢？
I don't understand.
我也不清楚
Let's take a look at this.
我們來看一看
Now this error is a little hard to understand but
這裡的錯誤有點難理解，不過
basically what it's saying is that you're calling
大概意思是說，你使用的這個
performOperation here with an argument which is a function,
performOperatin 是個函數，它接受一個函數作為一個參數
it only takes on argument.
但是這個函數只有一個參數，正常的應該是有兩個參數
Goes Swift looks here and
Swift 編譯器檢查了一個閉包
it's used that it's only using a dollar zero so
發現這個函數參數只使用了一個參數 $0
this is a one argument function this whole
也就是說這個函數只有一個參數
curly brace thing is a function that is one argument.
大括號里只有一個參數
Well four operation takes a function that
上面的四個運算調用的這個 performOperation 函數
has two arguments.
有兩個參數
So that's a mismatch that doesn't work.
所以參數個數不匹配，導致了這個錯誤
So how can we fix this.
那麼我們來修復這個錯誤
Well actually believe it or not we can just make a copy of
不管你相不相信，我們直接複製這個函數體
form operation of another method, same name.
相同的函數名字
This one we are gonna have different arguments.
但是這個函數與原來的函數有不同的參數個數
It's gonna have a, an argument which is
將只有一個參數
a function that only takes one double and returns a double.
只有一個 Double 參數，返回一個 Double 的值
And then inside here,
然後在函數體的內部
obviously we don't need topull two things off the stack,
顯然我們不需要彈出兩個元素
just one.
只彈出一個就行了
And obviously we only need to
同樣，我們只需要確保
check to make sure there is one thing on the stack.
棧中至少存在一個元素
And look, all error warnings gone, okay?
現在看一看，所有的錯誤都消失了，對吧？
So it automatically figured out that this
所以，它自動搞清楚
performer operation must be this one,
他必須匹配哪個 performOperation 的函數
because this is a function that only has one argument.
因為這裡只有一個參數 $0
And so it matched it up with this version of it.
所以它匹配了只有一個參數的函數的版本
So in Swift, you can have functions with the same name.
所以在 Swift 中，我們讓函數有相同名字
As long as they have different arguments.
只要他們有不同的參數就可以了
And that Swift will
Swift 的編譯器將會
automatically pick the right one, if it can.
自動選擇正確的一個
There are sometimes when it's just like,
某些時候這就好比
I can't really tell which one you mean.
你不告訴它你到底想要的是哪個
And it will certainly complain, in that case.
在這種情況下，它當然會發牢騷了（報錯）
But most of the type it's gonna be on [INAUDIBLE] from
但是，大部分情況
the types involved, what's going on.
它會通過參數類型判斷到底使用哪個函數
So, just gonna run this one again real quick.
讓我們運行一次這個程序
[INAUDIBLE] 36 square root.
輸入 36，平方根
Looks like it's working,9 times square root.
答案正確，再輸入 9，乘法，平方根
Excellent.
很好
Okay.
明白了嗎？
All right. So,
我們繼續
the last thing I'm going to do here is work on
我們要做的最後一件事
the layout of these buttons.
就是設置這些按鈕的佈局
So that's all I'm gonna do for the code.
我用代碼寫的就是這麼多
You can see that we really didn't have to
你可以看到，我們實際上
write that much code.
並沒有寫太多代碼
To make this work and
來讓這個應用運行起來
we got to do a lot of stuff in our UI here.
我們而是在 UI 上做了很多事
So, let's go ahead and make it so these buttons spread out.
讓我們繼續，把這些按鈕位置重新擺放
Cuz right now you see all this space is wasted right here.
因為你現在可以看到，我們浪費了很多空間
And on an iPhone in portrait mode.
如果 iPhone 在竪屏的時候
Whole bottom space is wasted.
我們下面的空間都浪費了
And an iPhone on landscape mode,
如果 iPhone 在橫屏狀態
this whole size can be wasted.
這塊區域被浪費了
So I really want these buttons much bigger, and
所以我很想把這些按鈕弄得大一些
stretching out.
拉伸開
Now, when you do something like that, you have to think
現在，如果你想做類似這樣的事情，你需要認真
a little bit of kind of what your strategy is gonna be.
思考一下到底應該怎麼做比較合適
You can't just kinda root four start, you know,
而不是急匆匆就開始隨便就開始
control drag it between things.
用鼠標隨便拖動這些按鈕之類的
And trying to set up the horizontal spacing,
或是試著設置水平間距
and maybe line up the, make the equal width and height.
或是對齊這些線，設置相同的寬度和高度
Oh my gosh, you'd be control dragging all day long,
要是這麼做你肯定得用鼠標拖一整天
by doing that.
So I'm not going to use control drag to do this.
所以我不會使用鼠標拖動來做這些事
I'm going to use these buttons down here which will kind of
我們將使用下面的這些按鈕來佈局
bulk out a layout buttons.
這些按鈕稱之為佈局按鈕
Let's go ahead and use the whole screen here.
我們先把這個界面擴大到全屏
Document outline.
把左邊欄關掉
So what is going to be my strategy?
那麼，我的策略是什麼呢?
Well, my strategy is I'm going to make a perfect grid here.
我的策略就是在這做一個完美的網格
So, I almost have one, except for there's one missing here.
目前已經差不多了，不過左下角還缺一個按鈕
So I'm actually going to take a button, copy and paste it.
所以我要複製一個按鈕，然後粘貼在左下角的這個位置
Okay, just kind of be a dummy button here actually.
把這個當做一個佔位按鈕就行了
With no title.
不用添加任何標題
I'm going to right click on it also because I don't want it
然後右鍵單擊這個按鈕，因為我不想讓它
sending appendage or anything else, So
和 controller 里的任何 Action 或者屬性關聯
its not going to send any messages.
現在，它就不會發送任何消息了
But it's just a dummy, so I'm kind of using.
現在我得費點
A little bit of brains over brawn here to do
腦筋來思考下這裡的佈局
this perfect grid.
這個完美的網格佈局
Now if I have this perfect grid, then if I had a rule
現在我已經有了這個網格，接下來我需要一些規則
where all these buttons had to be the same size, and they all
例如，這些按鈕需要相同的大小尺寸
had the same spacing between their neighbors, not just.
所有的按鈕都要和他相鄰的按鈕
Between each other but the same spacing to this edge and
有相同的間距，還要和這個邊界
the same spacing to this top edge.
或者頂部有相同的間距
Okay, if I had a rule like that then they would get
如果我有這麼一個規則，那麼
big and of course the spacing is facing from this edge
我們的按鈕自然就會稀疏並且
to edge and this edge to this edge.
與四邊有相同的間距
If it was all the exactly the same, which I'll make it be
如果這些按鈕都有相同的規則
whatever this is, whatever the dash for the lines gave me.
那麼無論這個按鈕是什麼
If that was the same then they would all have to spread out.
如果是規則一樣的話，他們將都延伸開來
Okay, they'd get bigger but
好的，按鈕之間會變的更稀疏，但是
they'd all stay the same size because I'm going to
我希望他們的尺寸都保持現在的大小，因為
make a rule that they have to be the same size.
我將制定一個規則來使他們保持大小
But they would move out to this edge so
但是這些按鈕將移到這邊
that this nearest neighbor would be the same, you know,
並且最近的元素保持相同的距離
this distance would be the same as this distance.
例如這個按鈕到右邊的間距將和它到它左側按鈕的間距是一樣
So that's my strategy, I'm going to try to do that.
這就是我的想法，我們嘗試一下
Now to make that work,
現在就開始
all these buttons need to know who their nearest neighbor is.
所有這些按鈕需要知道他們的最近的元素是誰
Well, these all know their nearest neighbor here,
好，這些都知道他們的最近的元素
the other buttons, because I made sure I used dashed
也就是其他按鈕的，因為當我拖拽它們時
blue lines when I dragged them in there.
我確保使用的藍色虛線來對齊它們
So, that's what kind of
這也是某種
teaches them their nearest neighbor.
確定它們最近的元素的一種方式
And I'm also going to make sure that the entire grid
接下來，我要確保整個網格
knows that the left edge and
知道它的左邊界
just under the label there, our nearest neighbor.
並且，知道它就位於這個標籤的下面
So now it knows on the top,
現在，它知道
the nearest neighbor is the label, and
離它最近的頂部元素是這個標籤，並且
on the left is this edge.
離它最近的左邊元素是這個邊界
And it's going to pick this edge as
我們要做的就是讓這些按鈕知道，右側的邊界是離他們最近的右側元素
the nearest neighbor for these buttons and the bottom edge,
底部的邊界是離他們最近的底部元素
cuz that's all there is and
因為這兒沒有其他的東西
nothing else out here that's gonna become,
可以成為這些按鈕的最近的元素
that's the only neighbor there is, it's gonna pick those.
它們只能選擇這兩個邊界
So now that I've used my dash for
那麼，現在我已經使用這些虛線
the lines it makes this all quite easy.
這將變的很容易
Now, if you don't use the dash for the lines, or
如果你不使用這些虛線
if you make some mistakes then it's not going to work.
或者你搞錯了什麼的話，它就不會有效的
This strategy won't work and I've made doing this part of
我做的這部分展示
this demonstration be extra credit.
是額外的
And so if you can't get it, don't worry about it too much,
因此，如果你不能做到或者不明白的話，也不必太擔心
just keep all your buttons in the upper left corner here
只需保持你所有的按鈕在左上角
and that's fine.
這就好了
But if you want to give this a try, the key is to
但是如果你想嘗試一下我所做的
use the dash lines to make the perfect grid.
重點是使用虛線，來確保整個按鈕網格是對齊的
Make sure that you set the nearest neighbors here by
同時通過拖拽整個網格確保你將左側邊界和這個標籤
dragging the whole grid to make blue lines appear on the sides.
設置為離這些按鈕最近的上部元素和左側元素
And then, we are going to set these rules in bulk and
然後，我們來設置這些規則
we do that with these buttons down here.
我們可以用下面的這些按鈕
So there's this button right here the left most button and
在最左邊的這個按鈕
it let's you set things like lining up leading edges or
它可以設置左邊對齊
the tops or the centers.
上邊對齊或者居中
And you could imagine there might be a way to do this by
也許你能想到，利用這些，可以實現我們想要的佈局
doing that but I am not going to use that strategy.
但是我們在這裡不會這麼做
My strategy is just make them the same size and
我的方法就是讓它們的大小一樣
make the space in between them, be the same.
並且它們之間的間距也一樣
But, I bet there's probably a way to do it by
但是，我相信，也許通過中點的方式
lining up their centers, or something like that, too.
或者類似的方式也可以做到一樣的效果
So I'm not going to use this one.
因此，我這裡不打算使用個按鈕
The next one over,
下一個按鈕
right here, is the one that has the things I want.
這裡就有我想要的東西
And so you can see that it'll ask you to
正如你所看見的，它會讓你選擇
make all the buttons equal widths and heights.
是否讓所有按鈕的寬度相等、高度相等
Okay, not width and
沒有勾選的這兩個選項（Width，Height）
height, that fixes them at a certain width and
是用來將它們修改成某個特定的寬度和高度的
height, this means that there,they can be any width and
但是這裡的意思是，對於所有的這些按鈕，寬度和高度可以是任意的值
height they want, but they all have to be the same width and
但是他們必須擁有相同的寬度和相同的高度
height all these buttons.
Of course I had these all selected by the way, if you
當然，我把這些按鈕都選中了
don't have them selected it doesn't make any sense.
如果你沒選中那就不會應用這些規則
And then up here, you can see there is spacing to
然後在這裡，你可以看到這是一個 Spacing to
nearest neighbor, so this is where I am going to set
nearest neighbor 的面板，我們把這些
that spacing between all these, to be the same.
按鈕之間的間距設為一樣
And you can see that it's put eight here.
正如你所看到的，這裡設置為 8
That's because when I did the dash lines
這是因為當我使用虛線對齊元素時
to the top eight seems to be kind of a standard number of
標準的間距就是 8 個像素點
points between elements.
These are all multiple because some of these buttons,
這裡顯示所有的左間距為 Multiple，那是因為這些按鈕中
their nearest neighbor is way over here and it's huge.
有些最近的元素是右邊界，這是一個巨大的數值
All right.
明白了嗎？
The bottom or their right.
最近的下邊元素和右邊元素的數值不一樣導致 Multiple
But all these buttons,the thing on top,
所有這些按鈕，最近的上部元素
whether it's another button or whether it's this label,
無論是另一個按鈕或者是這個標籤
all of them happen to be this eight points right here.
他們的間距都是 8 個像素點
So I want all of these to be eight.
我想讓這些都設置為 8 個像素點
So I'm just going to turn this bar on right here, which says,
在這裡我們打開這一欄
yes please enforce, and make the rule that all of
「 請確保這些所有
these are 8 points from their nearest neighbor to the top.
按鈕的到距離它頂部最近元素距離為 8 個像素點 」
And also, 8 to the left,8 to the right, and
同樣，左邊間距為 8 個像素點，右邊間距為 8 個像素點
8 to the bottom.
底部間距也為 8 個像素點
Really wanna make sure these beams are on,
確保這裡是打開的
if these beams are off,even if there's a number here,
如果他是關閉的，即使這裡有數字
then it's not gonna add this rule.
也不會添加規則的
So we wanted to add this rule.·
我們想要添加這些規則
So this adds up to
87 different rules.
所以總共有 87 個不同的規則
All these equal widths and
所有相同寬度，相同高度
heights and all these So if you don't have 87 in here,
以及這些，如果你的規則的數目不是 87
if it says a hundred and something,
假如是 100 或者其它，
probably you don't have everything lined up right.
那麼很可能你沒有將所有東西正確對齊起來
It only takes 87 constraints to express all these rules.
只需要 87 個規則就可以表示我們想要的網格佈局
All right.
明白了嗎？
Now, when I click this Add 87 Constraints it's
現在，如果我按下 「Add 87 Constraints」
going to add these rules to all these buttons, and
就會在這些按鈕上添加這些規則
watch what happens.
看看會發生什麼
So, I get all kinds of,
嗯，我得到了很多的線
first these blue lines are showing me the rules.
首先這些藍色的線表示規則
'Kay? A lot them are saying here
許多藍色的線代表這裡
that things are equal widths and heights.
的按鈕都是相同長度和寬度的
So these are what equals rules means.
這就是 equals 規則的意思
But there's also tiny little I beams right up here.
這裡還有一些小的 I 形狀的線
That are showing this basing to nearest neighbor, and
I 行的線表示以最近的物體為基準
also like there's a yellow, yellow here.
這裡還有一些黃色的線
This yellow, remember, means yeah,
記住，這些黃色的線代表
there's constraints on these, but they're not actually where
這裡雖然有一些規則，但是這些東西的位置本不應該
they're supposed to be based on those rules.
放置在這裡，也就是說，目前的位置和預想的位置有偏差
So we really want to move them all to be in their
我們很需要將這些按鈕，按照這些規則
proper spaces based on these rules.
移動到合適的地方
That's what these dashed yellow lines mean.
這就是這些黃色的線的意思
So we can do the same thing to do that,
我們可以像按剛開始
that we did at the beginning with the label on the top
處理頂部的標籤那樣
which is go to our document outline here,
點擊左下角的 document outline 菜單
in the lower left corner.
Okay these are document outline when we last saw it,
這些是 UI 文檔的縮略圖，上一次我們查看時
it only had this one label in there.
只有這一個標籤在這裡
Now we got all these buttons added.
現在把所有的按鈕都添加上來了
And you can see they're all selected.
而且你看到這些按鈕都處於選中狀態
All selected here as well.
在 Storyboard 中也處於全部選中的狀態
And, we've got this little yellow thing up here.
這上面有一個黃色的小箭頭
Now, if this is red, okay, if you do all this and
如果這裡是紅色箭頭，如果你做了之前的這些操作
this is red, well that means that you've got not just
並且是紅色箭頭，那就意味著你所添加的
warnings that your constraints aren't in the right place, but
規則不僅是警告，警告你目標的位置和預期的規則不同
you've got errors, usually conflicting constraints,
而且有錯誤，錯誤通常是由規則之間的衝突所引起
where you've asked auto layout to
當你讓自動佈局強制
enforce two rules that conflict with each other.
實施兩種相互衝突的規則時
So if you get to that red, this is not going to work.
所以如果箭頭是紅色，這些規則就不會正常工作
So, you'll want to start over, and
這是，你可能想重新再設置一遍
I'll show you in a minute how you can start over if things,
我稍後為大家展示怎麼再重新開始
or not going your way, but if it's yellow that just means
如果和你想的不同，黃色箭頭
things were in the wrong place.
僅代表有些東西在錯誤的位置
So no problem, we click the yellow.
很簡單，點擊黃色箭頭
Here's all the things that were in the wrong place.
這裡是在錯誤位置的東西
This is all the buttons,
這是所有的按鈕
you can see they highlight as I mouse over them.
你可以看到當鼠標移到按鈕上時，對應的按鈕高亮
And you can really pick on any one of them to fix this
你可以任意選一個來修改
because there's a nice little switch here called apply to
因為這裡有一個很方便的復選框，它代表
all views and containers.
將修改應用到所有視圖（views）和容器（containers）
You don't have to click on each one and
你就不必每一個都點擊
have it to frame update to the proper thing.
使它的 frame 更新到合適的大小
You can just click quite obvious in container and it's
你可以很容易的選中復選框
going to move the frame of all the buttons to fix the fact
這樣就會移動所有按鈕的 frame，修改
that they're in the wrong place based on their rules.
那些處於錯誤位置的
So let's try that.
讓我們試試看
I'm gonna hit this button here, Fix Misplacement.
我要點擊這個按鈕，「Fix Misplacement」
And it moved them all.
所有的按鈕都移動了
There's no more yellow.
沒有黃色的警告了
There's no auto layout issues.
沒有自動佈局的問題了
Okay. All looks good here.
看起來不錯
We can close our document outline.
可以關閉 document outline 視圖了
We zoom out, we can see, wow, it spread them all out.
將視圖縮小，可以看到按鈕充滿了整個視圖
Okay? Because,
maybe it's obeying those rules I gave it.
因為他們都遵守我定下的規則
Okay?
So let's now run this on some devices here and
現在，試試在不同的設備上運行
see what this looks like.
看看結果會怎樣
So turn off on an iPhone 6, which is a pretty tall device.
在 特別長的 iPhone 6 上
It's made, you know, kind of tall and thin.
iPhone 6 做的既長又窄
So if this still works fine enter.
一切正常
69874 times 5 divide maybe square root something like
輸入 5，enter，69874，乘法，5，除以，開平方根
that, it all seems to be working.
看起來運行正常
Now, not only is it working here in this portrait mode,
自動佈局不但在 iPhone 竪屏時工作正常
tall and thin.
既長又窄的情況
But if we go over here to this we can rotate the device.
如果我們從這裡旋轉設備
Okay, so I'm going to rotate left and
我要通過 ⌘ + 左，右鍵來
right and use the command keys to do this.
旋轉設備
And we rotate it right and you see it
設備向右轉可以看到
may the buttons spread out to this new location and
按鈕均勻分布到新的位置
we can rotate back using the command keys here.
可以用 ⌘ + 左，右鍵將設備轉回來
And it looks good in either orientation.
可以看到，在兩個方向上看起來都不錯
And in fact, it can look good on other devices as well.
實際上，在其他設備上同樣看起來很棒
So let's go over here and
點擊這裡
instead of doing iPhone 6, let's try it on an iPhone 4S.
這次不用 iPhone 6，試一下 iPhone 4S 上的效果
Okay so,
gonna switch the simulation here, let's run that.
切換模擬器，運行
Now the iPhone 4s, you can see is a little shorter,
現在是 iPhone 4S，它看起來短一點
it's not quite as tall.
並沒有那麼長
A little lower resolution, obviously.
很明顯，分辨率也有些低
But it relayed out the buttons to look good in that case too.
但是在這種情況下也將按鈕的位置擺放的很棒
9 times 9, divided by 8, square root, et cetera.
輸入 9，enter，9，乘法，8，除法，開平方等等
And same thing here we can rotate and
同樣我們可以旋轉
look at this one as well.
這樣看起來也不錯
Okay.
明白了嗎？
All righty.
好的
So the last thing I just want to talk about briefly is if
最後我想簡單說下
you try this extra credit and it doesn't work for you.
你嘗試得到額外加分，這是行不通的
Get all messed up, you can kind of start over by clicking
打亂所有限制，你可以通過點擊
on this and using the third button over here on the right.
這個位置並使用右邊第三個按鈕重新開始
And this allows you to reset your constraints and
這裡允許你重置你的約束，
you can see the top section here is the selected views.
你能看到上面的部分是被選中的視圖
I don't have any selected here so
我這裡沒有任何選中的視圖，因此
this wouldn't do anything right now.
現在這裡不能做任何操作
But the bottom is all views in container and
但是下面的部分是容器內的所有視圖
I kinda recommend going down here to all views
我推薦到下面所有視圖
container and clearing the constraints entirely.
容器內並清除所有約束
Reset to suggested constraints and try and
重置到建議的約束條件,
make some sense of your dashed lines but if it's not working,
但如果不工作，
you're probably, you're dashed lines are off anyway.
你很可能，
So you can just go here and
因此你僅僅需要到這裡
Clear Constraints, that'll clear them all.
清除所有約束條件，這將清除所有限制
Now that's gonna clear not just your buttons but
現在不僅僅需要清除你的按鈕，而且
also it's gonna clear your labels.
需要清除你的標籤
So you'll have to reposition your label with blue lines and
所以你必須使用藍色線條重新放置你的標籤並且
use control drag to say your top space, and, and
拖拽來確定你上部的空間
all that stuff, you know?
所有東西，瞭解？
If your buttons are really huge, they got really huge,
如果你所有按鈕確認很大，他們會變得很大，
but they're not in the right place, you can actually change
但是他們不能在正確的位置，你可以根據實際情況在工具窗口中調整
the size of all your buttons in the utilities window.
你的按鈕的大小
You can go to the size inspector right here,
有可以到尺寸查看器這裡
that's this one, you can actually type in the width and
這個位置你可以輸入所期望按鈕的實際寬度和
the height you want the buttons to be, make them
高度，確保他們
smaller again, which, you know, maybe 64 by 64.
再次變小，就像你所知道的那樣 可能是 64 x 64
That might make them easier to re-drag them into position so
這可以是他們變得容易再次拖拽到適當位置，
the blue lines are working.
藍色線條正常工作
And don't forget the very important blue line dragging,
不要忘記這個很重要的藍色線條的拖拽，
which is you want to take the whole grid and drag it,
你想要拖拽掙個格欄，
so that it's sitting underneath your label.
以至於它在你標籤下方
If you have problems dragging the whole grid underneath your
如果你拖拽你標籤下面的整個格欄有問題，
label, sometimes it's a good idea, clear all
通常清除所有約束限制是個好的做法
your constraints, kind of move your buttons out of the way,
移動你的按鈕到遠處，
just kind of move them down to the bottom here and then
僅僅移動他們到底部，然後
just for your label, do reset to suggest your constraint.
對你的標籤，做重置到建議的約束條件
This top one selected view
最上面那個被選中的視圖，
Rest Suggestion Constraints cuz that will work for
重置建議的約束條件英文這將對你的標籤起作用
the label if you move it into position as long as
你可以移動他倒適當位置只要
the buttons aren't too close and it thinks that, you know.
按鈕們不要靠的太近
Those buttons are near neighbors or something.
這些按鈕是進鄰或者其他什麼
And sometimes resetting it to suggest the constraints will
一些情況，重置到推薦約束
make it so that, that bottom edge of your UI label will
能做到，UI 標籤下邊緣是
be attainable when you drag your buttons into position.
可以達到的，當你拖拽一個按鈕到一個位置
But again, not to
但是，不要
worry too much about this auto layout stuff.
太擔心界面自動佈局的內容
It's extra credit in assignment one.
這是作業一的額外加分
It's not going to be extra credit in assignment two,
到了作業二就不是額外加分了
so you're eventually going to have to do it.
最終你都要做這件事
I'm going to be giving a big lecture on this in a couple of
我將花好幾個星期給你們好好講一下
weeks, on auto layout.
自動佈局
I've really just shown you just kind of what it can do,
我僅僅向你們展示了它的小小一角
I haven't really taught you how to do
我以前沒有教你們如何設置
auto layout in particular.
自動佈局
Auto layout is very important because we work in this
自動佈局十分重要因為我們
square area and
在這個方框被做工作
we want our UIs to work on all kinds of different devices.
我想要我們的界面能再各種不同設備上正常工作
That's why we're starting off in the very
這也是我們用它
start with some experience with it.
作為入門的原因
All right.
好了
So that is it.
就這樣
Now, later today, I'm gonna, in this lecture,
稍後，這次課中
I'm gonna give you a talk about this design paradigm
我將要給你講關於設計模式
called model-view-controller, and we actually designed our
叫做 模型 - 視圖 - 控制器，事實上我們設計的
calculator kind of poorly, because all of
計算器很差，因為這裡的所有
this code here is really nothing to do with UI.
代碼和界面沒有任何關係
This is all calculator brain, calculator engine code.
這是所有計算器的核心，計算器的引擎代碼
And this really wants to meet a different object and
這裡需要接觸一個不同的對象，
that's what MVC is all about.
這也就是 MVC
And so I'll give a little talk about MVC later today.
今天稍後我將講關於 MVC 的內容
And then on Monday, we're going to fix our calculator
然後再週一，我們將要解決我們計算器的問題，
to obey MVC and be a proper citizen in the iOS world,
達到遵循 MVC 架構，並成為 iOS 世界里的一員，
where all apps need to obey model V controller paradigm.
在這裡所有的程序都需要遵循 MVC 模式
>> So let's try and
understand for, I mean half of
來讓我們嘗試並理解，據你們說過半的人
you said that you already know MVC or you've seen it
知道 MVC 或者在其他
somewhere else so, this is going to be mostly review.
地方聽過它，因此這裡將是復習
But the other half of you, this will hopefully give you
另外一半人，這裡將給你
an idea of what MVC is all about.
一個 MVC 相關的概念
So MVC is basically a mechanism where we divide up
MVC 是一個基本機制，用於分類
all the objects in our application into one of
程序中的所有對象到
these three camps.
三個營地中的任意一個
Okay?
瞭解？
So, the three camps.
三個營地 （或者叫三層）
On the left there you see the model.
在左邊你看到的是模型
So, the model camp is gonna be all the objects that are what
模型層是那些對象的集合，這些對象是
your application does.
是程序的行為
So, for our calculator its, it calculates.
在我們計算器中，計算是模型
Okay, that's what it does.
那是計算器要做的
So, all the parts what we're doing perform operation, and
我們用於做執行操作的部分，和
all that stuff, that's all kind of calculator stuff.
相關材料，也就是計算器相關的內容
That should be in a calculator object somewhere else,
那些應屬於計算器對象
it shouldn't be in our controller.
不應該在我們的控制器中
And then the second camp is the controller, the controller
第二個陣營叫做 controller ，controller
controls how the model is presented on screen.
控制模型是如何顯示在屏幕上
And the view is the minions, the classes that
視圖是 controller 要
the controller is going to use are kind of
用到的的附屬類，有點類似於
like the the building blocks, the Lincoln Logs,
像積木，林肯積木，
I know maybe that's before all of your time.
我知道這也許是在你所有的時間。
But, you know, these things we're gong to do to build our
但是，這些事情是我們構建我們界面
UI, we're going to use in the view.
要做的事，我們在 view 中要用到它
So the stuff that's in the view is pretty generic, okay,
在 view 中的內容是相當通用的
generic UI elements.
的界面元素
The stuff in the controller is very specific to
在控制器中的內容是明確的，指出
how your UI works.
你的界面元素是如何工作的
And the stuff in the model is completely independent of
模型中的內容完全獨立於
how your UI works.
界面如何工作的
Okay?
懂嗎？
So doing MVC right is about knowing where things go but
因此正確的 MVC 不僅僅知道內容的存放位置而且
also about how to communicate between these three camps.
知道三層（camps）是如何通訊的
And so we can try and summarize how
我們來嘗試總結，
the communication works between these camps, and
三層之間是如何通訊的，
I've used road markings, you see the double yellow line and
我使用路面標線做講解，你看到的黃色雙線和
then the dashed white line.
白色虛線
So that's like you're driving in your car.
就像你駕駛你的汽車
Try to use them as an image for how this communication
嘗試用做以道路標線想象是如何通信的
happens, where it's allowed, where it's not allowed.
哪裡是允許通信的，哪裡是不被允許的
So let's talk about the Controller talking to
這樣，我們描述控制器是如何與
the Model.
模型
Going from that side of the road over to the Model side is
從控制器這側到模型 (Model) 這側是
a dashed white line, in other words,
白色虛線，換句話說，
you can head right across there.
你可以軋過虛線到另一側
You probably want to look before you go, but
你可能需要在你過對面之前觀察一下，但是
you can go right across, okay?
你可以正常穿越，對嗎？
The controller has to know everything about the model,
控制器必須瞭解 Model 的一切行為，
and it has to have complete ability to talk to
而且必須完全有能力和
the model, use its public API as much as it wants
模型（Model）通信，根據控制器需要，使用模型的開放 API
because the controller's job is to present the model to
因為控制器的職責就是展示模型（Model）給
the user using its view as its minions.
用戶，其視圖作為它的對象
So it has to have this access.
因此你必須有該權限
That full, unrestricted access the controller has talking to
控制器擁有的完全訪問權限可以與
the model.
模型通信
This is a one way arrow.
這是個單向箭頭
Control, or
控制器
one way arrow, from the controller to the model.
對模型的控制也是單向的
And similarly, from the controller to the view,
類似的，也可以從控制器到視圖，
is also unlimited communication,
也是允許通信的
because the controller is responsible for
因為控制器負責通過自身對象
talking using it's own minions.
向視圖發送指令
The view is, the controller's new meaning is
視圖是控制器設計
to lay out the user interface and all that stuff.
用戶界面的新方式
So, the controller can do anything it wants.
因此，控制器可以做任何它想做的事
I put that little green word, outlet,
我放置了一個綠色小字 Outlet 在上面，
up there because when we have a property of a controller
因為當我們有一個控制器的屬性，
that points into the view, we call it an outlet, okay?
該屬性指向視圖，我們稱它為 Outlet，懂嗎？
And you're gonna see that in the demo on Wednesday.
我們週三的展示中將要看到它
I'm gonna say, oh let's create an outlet from our controller
我想說的，讓我們創建一個 outlet， 從我們的控制器
to our view so
到我們的視圖
our controller can talk to it's view, all right?
這樣，我們控制器可以發送指令到對應視圖 對吧？
What about this communication?
這是如何通信的呢？
Model to view?
可以從 Model 到視圖嗎？
Never.
不可能！
And why is that?
為什麼會這樣呢？
100% obvious, the model is completely UI independent.
很明顯，Model 是完全獨立於 UI 的
So, there's absolutely no way it could talk to
因此，Model 沒有任何辦法向
a viewer object or anyone in that camp.
視圖對象發送指令，也不能和視圖層的任何對象通訊
Because the view objects are fundamentally UI objects.
因為視圖對象是基本的 UI 對象
They're kind of generic, but
他們是某種程度上是通用的，但是
they're still fundamentally UI objects.
他們也是基本的 UI 對象
Similarly, since the view objects are kind of generic,
同樣地，既然視圖對象是通用的對象，
they can't be talking to any specific model.
他們就不能和任何特定的 Model 對象通訊
They need a controller to interpret a model
他們需要用一個控制器來傳到信息
for them, okay?
懂嗎？
So there's never any communication this way.
因此這裡沒有任何通信
That's why it's a double yellow line.
這也是這裡使用黃色雙線的原因
That's why these lines are red.
這是這些線是紅色的原因
That's why there's fire, okay?
這也是這裡用火標注的原因 明白？
Never go across that line, Never.
永遠不要跨越這條線， 絕不！
What about the view talking back to the controller?
那視圖怎麼樣向控制器發送指令呢？
You got these generic view objects, like buttons.
你得到這些通用的視圖對象，例如按鈕
Can they talk to the controller?
他們能與控制器通信嗎？
Well, yes, they can.
對，當然可以
But, they have to be careful because the view objects
但是你必須小心，因為視圖對象
are generic.
是通用的
So they can't really know much about the controller.
這樣，他們不能真正的瞭解控制器
So, they can only communicate back to the controller
因此他們只能用盲目的方式和控制器通信，
in a blind way where they don't know the class of
視圖並不知道他們所通信的類
the thing they're talking to, and in a structured way.
在什麼位置，並用一種結構化的方式和控制器通信
A way where we all agree we're gonna communicate this way
這是一種大家都認同的，視圖和控制器通信的
between the view and the controller.
方式
So, whats an example of a structured way?
那，有沒有是結構化的方式例子？
Well one is called target action.
其中一個方式叫做 Target 操作
So, the controller basically drops a target on itself, and
一般控制器本身寫一個 target
then it hands out an action, which is like an arrow,
然後分給出一個操作方法，想一個箭頭
to the view and says to the view,
指向視圖，並和視圖通信
okay, when you do what you do, like you're a button and
當你想做了一個操作，比如你是一個按鈕，
someone touches you or your a slider and
別人點擊了你，或者你是個拖動條
someone moves you, send me that action.
別人移動了你，給向我發送那個操作
Okay?
懂嗎？
So, in this way, the generic button or
這樣，用這種方式，通用的按鈕或者
slider is communicating back to the controller.
拖動條就可以反過來和控制器通信
It has no idea that it's a card game controller or
它不知道這是一個紙牌遊戲控制器還是
a space game controller.
一個空間遊戲控制器
It doesn't know what kind of controller it is.
它並不知道它是什麼類型的控制器
All it knows is that when something happens in itself,
它所知道的只是某一個事件何時在它身上發生
boom, it sends a message to the target.
它發送一個消息給 target
So that's a blind, simple, structured way for
這樣就是一個盲目的，簡單的，結構化的方式來做
the view to communicate with the controller.
到視圖和控制器之間的通信
Okay?
明白嗎？
But what about more complicated ways?
那什麼是更複雜的通信方式呢？
Sometimes the view, things are happening in the view
有時，發生在視圖上的事件
that are somewhat complicated, and
是比較複雜的，
the controller needs to be informed of what's going on,
控制器需要知道正在發生的事是什麼，
synchronizing what's happening.
同步正在發生的事件
And one way to think about this is these words I
理解這個的一種方法是我放著
put up here, will, should and did.
will, should 和 did 這些單詞，
When the view is kind of like,
當某種視圖
let's say I am in the scroll view and
就比如說是在一個 scroll 視圖中，
I am scrolling around, and I want to let the controller
我正在到處滾動，並且我想要讓控制器
somebody know that the user just did scroll.
知道用戶剛剛做了滾動操作
Okay? Or
懂嗎？或者
the user puts down the touch and is about to scroll, I want
用戶按住屏幕，將要滑動，我想讓
to let the controller know the user will be scrolling, okay?
控制器知道用戶將要執行滑動操作 懂嗎？
Or, the user puts the touch down and
或者用戶按住屏幕
the scroll viewer wants to know,
scroll viewer 需要知道
should I allow the user to scroll here, is that allowed?
是否允許用戶這裡執行滾動操作？
All those things, the scroll view itself might not
這裡所有的事情，scroll 視圖本身或許沒有
have enough logic to know the answer to those questions.
足夠的邏輯知道那些問題的答案
So what it does is, it delegates the authority to
那它做的事情是，它代理給
answer those questions to some other object.
其他對象來回答那些問題
Now, it doesn't know the class of that object.
現在，它並不知道那個對象的類是什麼
All it knows is that other object can
他知道只是另一個對象可以
answer these questions, will, should, did, this, that, or
回答這些問題，will, should, did, this, that, 或者
the other thing like, should allow scrolling.
其他事情，像是否允許滑動
Did scroll to point.
滑動到一個點
Things like that.
就像那樣
So those are the kind of
這些是這樣一類
methods you are going to see in these delicate protocols.
方法，你將要在那些代理協議中看到他們
Now, I know this here is 1, 6 a and b,
現在，我知道這裡是 1，6，a 和 b
do not teach protocols.
沒有教過協議，
How many people know what
多少人知道
the word protocol means an
object during a programming?
協議在編程中代表什麼對象？
I can see very few of you.
很少能做到
So, I will be teaching that.
這裡我將要講它
A protocol is just a blind way to talk to another object.
協議僅僅是 blind 和其他對象通信的方式
When I teach it,
我講了它以後，
you're gonna be like oh, yeah, I know what that is.
你將會明白，這知道這就是它
So we can really call it protocol or whatever.
我們實際上叫它協議，或者不管什麼了
But that's how we do delegation, okay,
但這是我們如何實現一個代理，
this blind communication.
盲目通信
Also another important thing is
另一個重要事情是
that views should not own the data that they're displaying.
視圖不應該持有他們展示的數據
They should not own it.
他們不應該持有數據
In other words, it shouldn't be a property inside of them,
換句話說，數據不應該作為視圖內部的屬性，
where that's the truth of that data.
這就是數據。
And the easiest example for this is, all the songs in
最簡單的例子就是，在
your iPod, on your iPhone or your iPad, right?
你 iPod,iPhone 或者 iPad 中的所有歌曲 對嗎？
You might have 10,000 songs in there.
你可能有 10000 首歌曲
So, if you have some kind of generic list view in
假如你有一些通用的視圖列表在你視圖中，
your view, you can't transfer all 10,000 songs to its
你不能傳遞 10000 首歌到它的
instance variables, and
實例變量中，並
expect it to hold 10,000 songs so it can list through it.
期望它來持有 10000 首歌，來展示給你看
A, that would be inefficient, and
第一，這樣做是很低效的，
B that information, those 10,000 songs belongs where?
第二，這 10000 首歌屬於哪一層？
In the model.
在 Model 層
Okay, because your song database is a model.
OKay，因為你的音樂數據庫是一個 Model
It has nothing to do with UI.
它和 UI 沒有任何關係
It's just a list of songs and artists and albums and
視圖僅僅是歌曲，藝術家，專輯和其他信息的一個列表
all that, it's in the model.
它在 Model 層
Some controller has to look at that database and
一些控制器必須查詢數據並
tell a view how to display all those songs.
告訴一個視圖如何展示這些歌曲
Okay?
懂嗎？
So, we need that communication to happen here and the view is
這裡，我們這裡需要通信產生, 視圖
displaying some sort of list, and you're touching down and
展示列表分類，並且當你按下屏幕，
you're flicking on the list and trying to see more songs,
你輕輕滑動列表，試圖查看更多歌曲，
how does that communication happen?
這些通信如何發生的？
And the answer is, we have another special kind of
答案是我們 有另一種特殊的
delegate, which we call a data source.
代理，我們叫它數據源
Now the data source doesn't do the will did should.
數據源並不做 will, did, should 的事
It's gonna be asking questions like count,
它將回答類似，數量
like how many songs are there?
像這裡有多少首歌？
And the controller looks in the model,
控制器查找 Model
10,000 response to the view.
把 10000 返回給視圖
There's 10,000. The view
這是 10000, 視圖
makes space internally for 10,000 things.
為 10000 歌開闢內部空間
It doesn't know what they are.
視圖並不知道這些歌曲是什麼
Moves the scroll bar indicator a little bit so
稍微移動滾動條
that you know where it is.
你便能知道它在哪裡
And then you start scrolling, flipping through it, and
當你開始滾動，輕滑動它，
it starts sending the message to the controller,
它開始發送消息給控制器
give me the data at line 150 next 10 items.
返回 150 行後面的 10 條數據
You see what I mean?
你懂我意思嗎？
And then you flick down some more.
然後你再往下輕輕滑動
Now it's saying 250, 10 more items.
現在顯示 250， 另外 10 條數據
And so the control is going back to the model and
控制器再次與 Model 通信，並
saying give me more, give me more data.
要求得到更多的數據
And it's providing it to the view in this blind way.
控制器用這種 blind 方式提供數據給視圖
So to see how the view is getting data from the model
來看一下視圖如何從 Model 得到數據,
through the controller in this kind of blind structured way.
是通過控制器用這種 blind structured 方式實現的
Okay?
懂嗎？
That makes sense to everybody?
每個人都明白嗎？
So data source is just a kind of delegate,
數據源只是一種代理
it's a specific kind of delegate for getting data.
它是一種特殊類型的用於獲取數據的代理
So you're gonna see that there are classes in iOS that have
因此你將在 iOS 中看到一些類，
a data source, and they usually also have a delegate.
他們有一個數據源，並且通常有一個代理
Most sophisticated classes in iOS have a delegate, the will,
大部分 iOS 高級類有代理，包括 will,
did, should, kind of things.
did, should, 等要做的事
Some of them have a data source,
其中一些有數據源，
it depends on whether they are showing a lot of data or not.
這取決於他們是否要顯示大量數據
Now simple data, like if I had a view, if I invented a view
一些簡單的數據，比如我給紙牌遊戲
for my card game called Playing Card View and
創建了一個叫 Playing Card View 的視圖
it just has a suit and a rank.
它僅有花色和點數兩點屬性
Okay, we're not going to do count data app for
我們不會為了花色和點數
just suit and rank.
進行計算
We are going to set those properties.
我們會把它們設置成屬性
And so the view then would have that data set in it but
所以 view 里會有設置好的數據，但是
it wouldn't be owning it.
它不會擁有這些數據
Right? The model would still be
model 仍然會是花色和點數的
owning the suit and
擁有者
rank, the view is just getting that data to present it.
view 僅僅是為了顯示而獲取那些數據
'Kay. So simple data,
所以對於簡單的數據，
we might transfer to the view but it's merely for
我們會把它傳遞到 view 里，但是
it to display it.
只是給 view 來顯示
Okay.
This all adds up to the controller's job being to
所以 controller 的工作就是
interpret and format the model's data for the view.
給 view 解釋並格式化這些 model 提供的數據
That's the controller's job.
這就是 controller 的工作
And when we do our demo,
在我們做 deomo 的時候，
I'm going to be marking like, oh see I'm writing this code.
我會在寫代碼的時候提示大家，
This is to make the controller perform its job,
這段代碼是為了讓 controller 執行它的工作，
which is to take the model data and
也就是從 model 中取出數據然後
using its view minion to put it on screen.
送到 view 中去，然後顯示到屏幕上
Okay? That's what
這就是
the controller does.
controller 做的事情
What about this communication?
那關於通信呢？
Can the model talk to the controller?
model 可以和 controller 通信嗎？
Again, obviously that's verboten because model knows
同樣的，顯然是不可以 因為 model 對於 UI
nothing about UI, so
一無所知，所以
it couldn't possibly talk to a UI object like the controller.
它不可能同像 controller 一樣的 UI 對象進行通信
But sometimes things change in the model, and
但是有些時候，model 中的數據變了，
the controller needs to know about it, okay?
controller 需要知道這個變化
Data changes, a database changes or
數據改變了，數據庫改變了，或者
the model is some network database, and
model 是網絡數據庫，
somebody changes something on the network and it changes.
某人在網絡上修改了數據，數據改變了
And the controller needs to find out.
controller 需要瞭解這些
So, how do we do that communication?
所以，我們怎樣進行這種通信呢？
We do that using kind of a radio station model.
這可以通過一種電台的模型來理解
Okay?
So, the model, a radio station concept, the model will use
所以，model 是一種電台的概念，
this concept to essentially broadcast information to
model 將會利用這一概念，把信息廣播給
anyone who's interested.
感興趣的任何人
Okay?
And the mechanisms for doing this in iOS are called
在 iOS 中為瞭解決這種問題而使用的技術我們叫做
Notification and Key Value Observing, KVO we call it.
Notification 和 KVO
And so, the model can just say, oh, anytime
所以，model 可以這樣，
something changes in my model I'm just gonna broadcast on
我當中的任何東西發生了變化，我會通過我的電台
my radio station, and then the controller simply tunes into
廣播一下，隨後，controller
that radio station, and he can find out things are changing.
會接收到來自電台的信息，它會發現數據在變化
And when he finds out something changes,
發現數據變化以後，
it's gonna communicate via its green arrow to the model and
它就會通過它的綠剪頭同 model 進行通信，
say, okay, give me that data that changed.
給我那個改變過的數據
Right?
That make sense?
能聽懂嗎？
So, towards the end of the quarter we'll start seeing
所以在課程快要結束的時候，我們將會學習
a little how to do notification to find out, for
如何利用 notification 得知
example, if the data in a database changes.
例如數據庫中的數據發生了改變
We'll get a notification, the UI can then, you know,
我們將會獲取一個 notification，UI 的 controller
controller can then go talk to the model to get the info.
隨後可以同 model 通信來獲取信息
Okay?
Some people have asked,
有些人會問，
can a view tune into the radio station?
view 可以接收廣播嗎？
They probably could, but
它們也許可以，但是
you probably wouldn't want to do that.
你最好不要這樣做
That would probably be a violation of MVC.
這可能違背了 MVC 的原則
All right.
So we do this.
我們這樣做，
We have all this nice communication and
我們有這些很好的通信方式和
all these rules,
所有的這些規則
and we can imagine building something simple using this.
我們可以利用這些來製作一些小的應用
But what if we wanna build a big complicated app?
但是如果我們想要製作一個巨大複雜的應用呢？
An app that has multiple screens on our iPhone, or
一個在 iPhone 或 iPad 上運行，有多個屏幕，
an iPad, it's got three or
在屏幕上有三個或四個不同的區域，
four different areas on screen where things are happening.
都發生著事情
How do we do that?
我們該怎麼做？
Well, we're essentially going to
我們會結合
combine multiple MVCs, okay?
多個 MVC
Because an MVC can use as part of its view, another MVC.
因為一個 MVC 可以將另一個 MVC 當做視圖的一部分
Okay?
So an MVC, an entire MVC can be one of
所以一個完整的 MVC 可以被一個稍大些的
the minions of some bigger MVC.
MVC 當做僕從使用
'Kay?
And by doing that and cascading it down,
我們可以一層一層地這樣堆疊，
we can build more and more complicated applications.
就可以製作出越來越複雜的應用
So, an example of this is, you might have your calendar app,
例如，你可能有一個日曆應用，
and it's showing you the entire year.
它展示給你一整年的信息
And you click on a month, and now it shows you a month view.
隨後你點擊了一個月份，於是它展示給你月視圖
Well, a month view looks a lot different than a year view.
月視圖看起來和年視圖就不太一樣了
A month view just has all the days and maybe some circle
一個月視圖只含有日期，也許在日期上
that tells you where you have an appointment on a day.
會有一些通知你在某天會有任務的圈圈
And then when you click on a day, and
隨後，你點擊了一天，然後你
now you get a day view, okay?
獲得了一個日視圖
And the day is showing you the hours and what all
日視圖會顯示小時信息和這天你的所有任務，
your appointments are, and you click on the Appointment now
隨後你點擊了任務，
you get an appointment view and it showing the detail of
你會獲得任務視圖，它會顯示任務的細節，
where you're going and when it is et cetera, okay?
將要去哪，何時動身還有其它一些東西
Well, each of those views, year view, month view, the day
這些 view 中的每一個，年視圖，月視圖，日視圖，
view, and the appointment view are their own MVCs.
任務視圖，都有他們自己的 MVC
Okay?
But you can see how the last three, okay,
但是你可以發現，最後三個 view,
are used as essentially a minion of the top level view,
都被最頂層的年視圖為了展示更多的細節
year view, to show more detail, okay?
而被當做僕從使用
So the year view,you click on a month,
所以在年視圖里，你點擊了一個月份，
it's going to use the month view MVC to show more detail.
它會利用月份視圖的 MVC 來展現更多細節
So it's part of its view,okay?
所以它是它視圖的一部分，
So, you see this also in iOS with tab bar
所以你也在帶有 tab bar 的 iOS 應用
controllers, right?
中見過這些吧
You have the tab bar at the bottom, I have four or
在底部有一個 tab bar，有四個或五個
five things you can choose.
項可以供你選擇
Well there's some MVC at the top whose has four pointers to
在上面有一個 MVC，它指向四個僕從，
four minions, which are the four MVCs that are each going
也就是將要出現在
to appear in a tab bar, okay?
tab bar 的 MVC，
We'll be doing that for
我們將會做一個這方面的 demo，
example, in assignment number two or
在第二次或第三次作業，我們會
three where we'll be making a tab bar and
製作一個 tab bar，
you're gonna have to do multiple MVCs, okay?
你們將會學習如何使用多個 MVC
So, that basically results in a picture looks kinda
所以使用多個 MVC 的效果看起來就像
like this.
這張圖片一樣
All right?
Where you got this MVC, and
在你看到的這個 MVC 里，
you see the purple one that's like underneath the word
找到'together' 下面的那個
together there, and
紫色的，
it points to three other MVCs outside of its view thing.
它從 view 指向了另外三個 MVC，
Okay?
That's how we're going to build it, so
這就是我們創建 tab bar 的方式，
that might be a tab bar control and
這些可能就是它的
those might be the three tabs.
三個標籤
Okay, and each one is its own little MVC
並且它們每一個都是
completely independent, operates on its own.
完全獨立的，可以獨自行動的小 MVC
Doesn't even know,
這時它就是一個
it's a generic reusable view like thing at this point.
普通的可重用的 view 之類的東西，
Doesn't even know that it's in a tab bar.
它甚至不知道它在 tab bar 中
Okay, it just knows that it's supposed to do
它只知道它應該做
whatever it does.
這些事情
And so it's modular in that way.
所以在這方面，它是模塊化的
You can also see that there's no communication between any
可以看到這裡不再有其他箭頭，
other, there's no other arrows, except for
除了
some of the models.
一些 model
You see some of the models are communicating with each other.
某些 model 之間在互相通信
You know a big
要知道，
application might have a single shared model.
一個大型的應用也許會有一個單獨的共享 model
Or the models might be split off into pieces to be used by
或者，model 會被分開來
sub MVCs.
供子 MVC 使用
Okay? But
但是，
that's the only kind of communication you have there.
這裡只能使用這種通信方式
All other communication is
其它所有的通信
either the structure view communication we saw on MVC,
要麼是 MVC 中的結構化通信，
or it's using MVCs as part of the view of another MVC.
要麼是將 MVC 用作另一個 MVC 視圖的一部分
Any question about that?
有問題嗎？
So we definitely don't want to be having designs that
所以我們當然不希望
look like this, okay?
設計成這樣，
Where everybody's talking to everybody.
所有都在互相通信，
We can't tell who's talking to what.
我們不能分清誰在和什麼通信
It's just impossible to debug a program like this, and
這會讓調試程序變得異常艱難，
it doesn't scale.
而且它無法規模化
You can't build really big programs this way.
你不能通過這種方式創建出大程序
It just becomes impossible to
這樣的話，
know how touching anything would break everything, right?
你無法弄清楚，什麼地方會引發整個程序的崩潰
So we're definitely not going to be doing that.
所以我們絕對不會這樣做的
All right so that's MVC and,
所以，這就是 MVC，
like I say, on Monday we'll apply MVC to our calculator.
我們將會在週一的課里把 MVC 應用到我們的 calculator 中
So what's coming up?
所以，接下來是什麼？
I always try to get to this slide every lecture.
我每節課都盡量講到這裡，
Sometimes I forget but it's posted in the slides.
有時我會忘記，但是它被放到了投影片中
It says tomorrow is Friday.
週五也就是明天，
No, day after tomorrow is Friday.
不對，後天的週五，
And people who are watching on iTunes U,
在 iTunes U 上觀看的同學們，
these Friday sections will not be on iTunes U so
週五的部分不會被放到 iTunes U 上，
don't go looking for them only the normal Monday,
只有週一和週三的才會被放上去，
Wednesday lectures went on iTunes U.
所以不要到處找
But, for Stanford students,
但是對於在坐的同學，
Friday we have this debugger section we talked about.
週五我們將討論之前談到的調試部分
And then next Monday,
下週一，你們的閱讀作業
your reading assignment is gonna be due.
將會截至
In other words, you should be done with that
換句話說，你應當在週一上課之前
reading assignment before the start of Monday's lecture.
完成閱讀作業
And I'm gonna assign you another reading assignment.
我會再佈置給你們一個閱讀作業
It might be your only other reading assignment.
它將會是你們最後一個閱讀作業
Perhaps there'll be a reassignment three,
也許以後還會有閱讀作業，
but it won't be any more than that.
但是不會像那個一樣多
And then on Wednesday I'm
下週三，我會深入介紹
really gonna dive into Swift and Foundation.
Swift 語言和 Foundation 框架
I'm gonna talk a little bit about the Objective C legacy,
我將會介紹一點遺留下來的 Objective-C
and then your assignment one is gonna be
你們的作業一將會在
due a week from today.
一周後截止
It's been posted for you, and your assignment two is gonna
你們已經看到了，作業二將會在
go out next Wednesday and be due the Wednesday after that.
下週三佈置下去，下下週三截止
Just for a little bit of advanced planning for
提前為你們所有人
all of you.
做一些計劃
Okay?
Any other questions?
還有問題嗎？
Okay, thank you.
好的，謝謝
>> For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.
>> 想瞭解更多，請登錄 stanford.edu